<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hugo Grotius his Sophompaneas, or, Ioseph a tragedy : with annotations / by Francis Goldsmith.</title>
            <author>Grotius, Hugo, 1583-1645.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 199KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B23779</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11295025</idno>
  <idno type="VID">205034</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240856758</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing G2125</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">11295025</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B23779)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 205034)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1462:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Hugo Grotius his Sophompaneas, or, Ioseph a tragedy : with annotations / by Francis Goldsmith.</title>
                  <author>Grotius, Hugo, 1583-1645.</author>
                  <author>Goldsmith, Francis, 1613-1655.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 102 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Iohn Hardesty ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1652]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date is given in the form of a chronogram in the translator's name: FranCIs GoLDsMIth.</note>
                  <note>Errata at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:205034:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:205034:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>HƲGO GROTIƲS</hi> HIS Sophompaneas, OR IOSEPH.</p>
            <p>A TRAGEDY.</p>
            <p>With Annotations.</p>
            <p>By FranCIs GoLDsMIth, Esq;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. H.</hi> and are to be sold by <hi>Iohn Hardesty</hi> at the Black-spred-Eagle in <hi>Duck-lane.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:205034:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:205034:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable, HENRY, Lord Marquess of <hi>Dorchester,</hi> Earl of <hi>Kingston,</hi> Viscount <hi>Newark,</hi> Lord <hi>Pierrepont,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ot any merit of mine hath emboldned mee to set forth this Piece with (so resplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent a Frontispiece) your Name; but a duty of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of our best modern Latin Poets that full right, which my pen otherwise comes short of. Bee pleased likewise, that <hi>Sophompaneas,</hi> a divinely inspir'd Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and Royall Favourite, famous in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Writ (which your own eminent vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues will most like) for wisdome and chastity, may find a favourable entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with your Lordship. I am not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant
<pb facs="tcp:205034:3"/> upon how great disadvantage any thing of this kind is presented unto your Lordship, after <hi>Iuvenal</hi> by Sir <hi>Robert Stapylton.</hi> Neither have I, though I much more need it, the warrant of your Lordships command, which might beg pardon for my disabilities and errataes: Yet that this free-will &amp; cheaper offering may be not unacceptable to your most noble goodnesse, and that this Coat of <hi>Ioseph</hi> is not so sullied with my handling, but that it may bee known, is the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and ambition of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordships most humble Servant, <hi>FRANCIS GOLDSMITH.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:205034:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>IF an account is to bee given the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, as <hi>Cato</hi> thought, even of our idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; take then, at thine owne leasure, this of mine. For such and no better may a grave Censor deeme it, though I write after a most learned Copy, and have the priviledge of a Divine Argument. Yea, I my selfe, had I not the allowance of some friends, both can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did and judicious, would sooner commit these Papers to the light of the fire, then of the Sun. It may likewise be a question perhaps, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an Interpreter deserve the name of a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et; but he, that is one indeed, a <hi>Virgil</hi> or <hi>Homer</hi> need not envy a <hi>Cicero</hi> or <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mosthenes.</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">I had rather saith <hi>Tacitus</hi> (or who else is the Author) in <hi>Dialog. d.
<pb facs="tcp:205034:4"/> Orator.</hi> have the secure and secret retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Virgil,</hi> wherein yet he neither wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the favour of <hi>Augustus Caesar,</hi> nor the being taken notice of by the People of <hi>Rome:</hi> Witness the Epistles of <hi>Augustus,</hi> witness the People themselves, who up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hearing some verses of <hi>Virgil</hi> in the Theater, rose all up, and did the same re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to <hi>Virgil,</hi> by chance then present, and a spectator, as unto <hi>Augustus.</hi>
               </q> Our Author is an excellent and admirable patterne, not onely for Poetry and Oratory, but all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and humane learning; I would gladly follow the best examples, and overtake them, when any other of my endeavours shall from the Father of lights (from whom every good and perfect gift commeth down) receive such a blessing.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:205034:4"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>To <hi>GERARDUS VOSSIUS,</hi> Professor of History and civill Arts, in the most flourishing City of <hi>Amsterdam,</hi>
               </salute>
               <signed>HUGO GROTIUS.</signed>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Were, most excellent <hi>Vossius,</hi> what I least would bee, that is, ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, if when all your papers are full of me, I should keepe the love and honour of you shut up within the closet of my minde, and take no care, that poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, if yet my labours may so hope, might have some monument extant of our inseparable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction; which you in my adversity, such as is wont either to discover false affections, or to change light, have been so far fron lessening, as that by many offices you have made it greater. If I should say, your learning indeed singular and infinite hath brought me to esteem you as I doe, I say but what is common to mee with the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versity of them through the whole world that love letters. But the nearer I have been admitted to know your most candid manners, and goodnesse
<pb facs="tcp:205034:5"/> shut against no man, I have alwaies thought it a great part of my felicity to bee joyn'd with you in so much a greater tie. The common study of all humane literature is a very strong bond: but I adde also, that in this ages fervent heat of Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall disputations, I have found you of that singular prudence and moderation of mind, as that from those things which the Churches plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Apostles, and which they who agreed with them in likenesse of discipline, have held as certaine and resolv'd, you would never depart; but from those, which of old have had a free dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, you would inhibit your decretory style. To hold which purpose more happily, you had two great helps at hand, a very great, and as much as ever had any man, diligence, and a pure judgement in revolving Ecclesiasticall An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquities; whereof no man can doubt who shall have read your Pelagian History, a worke most famous through <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Brittaine.</hi> To your so great virtues and merits towards me some extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary present was due: But whereas I could not as yet appoint a certaine seat for my hitherto scattered papers and bookes, and so not put my last and irrevocable hand to any of my greater workes; mindfull in the mean time of humane chances, though unable to pay, yet by giving e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a small pledge I would testifie how much and how gladly I am indebted. And yet if you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb facs="tcp:205034:5"/> me (what <hi>Horace</hi> allowes himselfe) to set a price upon my gift, it is a Tragedy I bring, a kind of writing (as you very well know, <hi>Vossius,</hi> of whom after precepts of Grammer and eloquence, we have also the art of Poetry expressed in lively colours) royall, and of so great dignity, as that <hi>Sophocles</hi> hath not thought it below his high place which he held in <hi>Athens;</hi> nor <hi>Augustus Caesar</hi> his owne minde comprehending the whole power of the Roman Empire. I may commend it too for the Argument fetcht not from the miseries of <hi>Troy</hi> and <hi>Thebes,</hi> polluted with the lies of the Grecians, but out of the History of <hi>Moses</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toucht by falshood: and indeed, unlesse I mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, the only one in Divine Writ, which hath those two things thought by <hi>Aristotle</hi> (a man in this part also, as you concurre with me, of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test judgement) even single to adde very much to the grace of a Tragedy; an unlook'd for Agniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and sudden change of things. For both <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seph</hi> discovers himselfe to his Brethren, who for a long while knew him not, and his Brethren themselves are suddenly translated out of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test fear into the highest prosperity. Some perhaps will find fault, that this Tragedy hath not a sad conclusion: who if they have not yet laid aside that error in distinguishing between the buskin and socke; let them read either <hi>Aeschy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi>'s <hi>Danaides,</hi> or our <hi>Euripides</hi> his <hi>Alcestes, Ion,
<pb facs="tcp:205034:6"/> Helena,</hi> and which I have lately turn'd into Latin, <hi>Iphigenia</hi> among the <hi>Tauri:</hi> or (if they will not take that paines) those your precepts I now men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned of the <hi>Art of Poetry.</hi> Wherunto, whether what I here present bee agreeable, I desire no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther judge then your selfe; not indeed upon confidence of my endeavours, which both by the cruelty hitherto of fortune and my declining age it selfe (whereof you almost alone are not sensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) begin to flag, but in the equity of your judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which yet I hope not for as a friend; for neither would I corrupt you in what I ought to offer unto you as precious, but as one who have propounded to my self ever to deserve the best of letters and lovers of letters. There is also in this argument another thing, which whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it will please others I know not, for wee live in a malignant age; that certainly it will please you, I doubt not. <hi>Philo,</hi> little lesse then a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, hath taught me, that <hi>Moses,</hi> whom both we and the Jewes (by the manifest evidence of what he foretold) believe to have bin divinely inspir'd, and who is celebrated for a most wise Law-maker by wise men, and born in a very wise age, <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus</hi> the Sicilian, <hi>Trogus Pompeius</hi> a Roman, and a Cappadocian indeed, but the most judicious, <hi>Strabo;</hi> when in the preamble of his most holy lawes he had given us three choice patterns for a private life, the first of him who by the aid of
<pb facs="tcp:205034:6"/> arts and excellent learning came from false gods to the true; the second, whose birth it selfe and happy education did very much advantage him; and a third, who besides these benefits had this also, which I by experience think the greatest, a triall by afflictions, would adde likewise a man exercised in publike government, notable, not onely for those hereditary and domestique vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, but what were also profitable to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth; which indeed in <hi>Ioseph</hi> he hath so perform'd, as that he, a leader of the people, if ever any, provident for the future, unbroken in evils, a maintainer of justice, observing mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in all things, may seeme to have set him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe no other copy, next to the divine Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, by which to order his actions, then the life of this <hi>Ioseph;</hi> far differing from those worst of men, and consequently of teachers, who when they would give us the Character of a Prince, are wont to make him a man compos'd of deceit and perfidiousnesse, and an obdurate contempt of God and all lawes, as wel common as peculiar, to any people; a constitution of mind, unlesse I mistake, not attainable, but through a long custome of villanies. But these things it is your part to prosecute more at large, of whom after your books the best guides unto, and Judges of the Greeke and Latin Annalists; wee all, who who love truth and right, I say not expect, for
<pb facs="tcp:205034:7"/> that is too little, but earnestly beg the sum also of Universall History. Farewell man nearest my heart, and comfort your want of a lost Sonne (since it hath so pleased God) with those many children of your learning, begotten by you, and sent abroad through the whole World.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Francfort.</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>The Ides of</hi> Iuly, 1634.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="addendum">
            <pb facs="tcp:205034:7"/>
            <head>Vossius in Addend. <hi>l.</hi> 2. Institut. Poetic.</head>
            <p>THe question is, whether it bee lawfull to make a Dramatique Poem of a sacred argument: if examples may be pleaded; <hi>Ezekiel</hi> a Iewish Tragique Poet, hath written the deliverance of the Israelites out of <hi>Egypt.</hi> There is likewise extant Christs Passion, whether by <hi>Gregory Nazianzen,</hi> or <hi>Apollinaris</hi> of <hi>Laodicea.</hi> Neither have there been wanting in our age famous men also, who have written sacred Dramatiques both Comicall and Tragicall: But I am rather of opinion, it were better to choose a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother argument, then sacred. For it agrees not with the majesty of sacred things to be made a play and fable. It is also a work of very dangerous consequence to min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle humane inventions with things sacred; because the Poet adds uncertainties of his owne, sometimes fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities; which is not onely to play with holy things, but also to ingraft in mens minds uncertaine opinions, and now and then false.—These things have place espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, when we bring in God, or Christ, speaking, or treat of the mysteries of Religion. I will allow more where the History indeed is taken out of the sacred Scriptures, but in the nature of its argument is civill. As if the action bee of <hi>David</hi> flying from his Sonne <hi>Absolon,</hi> or of <hi>Joseph</hi> sold by his Brethren; advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb facs="tcp:205034:8"/> by <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to the government of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and in that dignity adored by, and made known unto his Brethren. Of which argument is <hi>Sophompaneas,</hi> made by the most illustrious and incomparable man, <hi>Hugo Grotius,</hi> Embassador, when hee lived, of the most gracious Queen and Kingdome of <hi>Sweden,</hi> to the most Christian King of <hi>France.</hi> Which Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy I suppose may be set for a pattern to him that would handle an argument fetcht from the holy Scriptures; and I would even more commend it in this place, then which a fitter could not be; did I not fear, I might seem to do it as well in regard of that love, which was ever between us, as also in officiousnesse of a gratefull minde, forasmuch as hee would have this excellent Poem come forth into the light, dedicated unto my name.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:205034:8"/>
            <head>To his own old dear <hi>Francis Goldsmith,</hi> Esq;</head>
            <lg>
               <l>SO doth the toiling Husbandman at last,</l>
               <l>Feed full his longing mind, his eye, and taste,</l>
               <l>When once into his own hands he doth get</l>
               <l>That Pear or Plum which the same hands had set.</l>
               <l>A modest pride so flatters me, to see</l>
               <l>What was my kernell once, now grown a Tree.</l>
               <l>So on the Cart, the poor Fly doth out thrust</l>
               <l>Its Tiffan wings, as if it rais'd the dust.</l>
               <l>I thank'd thee thee for thy Catechisme before,</l>
               <l>But <hi>Sophompaneas</hi> much augments the score:</l>
               <l>His Brethren and his Fathers Father he,</l>
               <l>Brethren and Father both doth find in thee.</l>
               <l>Thou bringst him Spice, Balme, our best English Honey,</l>
               <l>And (in thy learned notes) bringst double Money.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jacob</hi> in <hi>Syria,</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> made him live,</l>
               <l>Another life in <hi>Britaine</hi> thou dost give.</l>
               <l>But how doth <hi>Grotius</hi> indebted stand</l>
               <l>To thee, that mak'st him Denison of our Land?</l>
               <l>Go on dear <hi>Frank,</hi> and let thy pious toil,</l>
               <l>Transport, translate, enrich our barren Soil</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:205034:9"/>
               <l>With all his spoiles, that are (all are) of worth,</l>
               <l>His <hi>Gallo-Belgick</hi> labours have brought forth.</l>
               <l>Teach us his <hi>Laws of war</hi> (but rather peace)</l>
               <l>Teach us his <hi>Christian Truth,</hi> that may encrease,</l>
               <l>And here produce of Faith a plenteous breed,</l>
               <l>(We have some Indians here stand much in need.)</l>
               <l>Teach us by him <hi>Gods word</hi> to understand:</l>
               <l>These Works, my <hi>Frank,</hi> call for thy worthy hand.</l>
               <l>In the mean time though more of thee we crave,</l>
               <l>We thankfully accept of what we have.</l>
               <l>This <hi>Joseph,</hi> and thy <hi>Catechising</hi> us,</l>
               <l>Shall stile thee new, rise <hi>Francis Grotius.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>—Mihi Nulla rura, at</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Spiritum</hi> Graiae <hi>tenuem Camaenae</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Parca non mendax De Dit, &amp; —</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:205034:9"/>
            <head>Somnium Dramaticum Synesii Iunioris, Cognomento CHIROSOPHI.</head>
            <l>THe evil of the Day had tyred light,</l>
            <l>Glad to fall into the darke armes of Night.</l>
            <l>When <hi>Moses</hi> sacred <hi>Genesis</hi> had fed</l>
            <l>My thoughts so full, that in my active Head</l>
            <l>The waking Phant'sie wrought the holy Theame</l>
            <l>Into the forme of a Dramatique Dreame.</l>
            <l>Me thought I saw fair <hi>Joseph,</hi> while they cry'd</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Abrech</hi> before Him, in great honour ride;</l>
            <l>The tender Father of the King proclam'd:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Zapnath-paaneah</hi> by great <hi>Pharo</hi> nam'd.</l>
            <l>I took three sips of his Divining Cup,</l>
            <l>Which heightned my Prophetique spirit up</l>
            <l>To such a pitch, that I could soon unfold</l>
            <l>All Secrets the Synesian Riddles hold.</l>
            <l>The silver Goblet (upon Arts command)</l>
            <l>Turn'd to refined Gold within his Hand;</l>
            <l>The Scenes were with all properties endu'd,</l>
            <l>Could heighten a Majestique Enterlude.</l>
            <l>The Acts (rehears'd) might reconcile the Stage</l>
            <l>To chaster ears, and purifie the Age.</l>
            <l>Things were so done; there did more lustre spring</l>
            <l>From his rich Buskin, then from <hi>Pharo's</hi> Ring.</l>
            <l>The Plaudit was so loud at every clause,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:205034:10"/>
            <l>I wakened with the Eccho's of applause.</l>
            <l>The Day return'd: upon my thoughts review,</l>
            <l>I found my Dream, in your Translation, true.</l>
            <l>So well perform'd: it will extend the Fame</l>
            <l>Of reverend <hi>Grotius,</hi> and advance Your name.</l>
            <l>Thus while with pious thoughts the learned strive</l>
            <l>To infuse new life, <hi>Joseph</hi> is yet alive!</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Increasing</hi> still for others, as of old,</l>
            <l>'Twill be his fortune to be bought and sold.</l>
            <l>But friend, I think 'twas the best chance of wit,</l>
            <l>To finde a Patron for the Poem sit.</l>
            <l>T' ignoble greatness for to prostitute</l>
            <l>Thy <hi>Joseph,</hi> did not with thy honour suite.</l>
            <l>Such who affect Effeminate extremes,</l>
            <l>Would make him blush for to expound their Dreames.</l>
            <l>Debauch'd and empty Lords, whose poppy heads</l>
            <l>Now Levell-switcht, fall to their earthly beds.</l>
            <l>But thou hast chose one, high, rich, learned, good,</l>
            <l>With all the virtues of enobled blood.</l>
            <l>Where worth doth over mens affections sway,</l>
            <l>There will the sons of Art their Tribute pay.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>CHIROSOPHUS</signed>
               <salute>Francisco Chrysergo Grotio, Amicitiae &amp; Cognominis Ergo.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:205034:10"/>
            <head>On the Subject, <hi>Joseph.</hi> The Poet, <hi>Hugo Grotius.</hi> The Translator, <hi>F. Goldsmith.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>JOSEPH!</hi> Thou Heir of Love! in whom wee find</l>
               <l>Fair <hi>Rachels</hi> Face, and holy <hi>Jacobs</hi> Mind.</l>
               <l>Their Darling, <hi>Egypts</hi> Idol, Heavens Delight,</l>
               <l>Both <hi>Pharaohs,</hi> and Jehovahs Favourite.</l>
               <l>Chast, Fair, Just, Great, None such Live in our Daies:</l>
               <l>We can but act thy Actions in Playes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>GROTIUS!</hi> Thy Exile was the Worlds good Fate,</l>
               <l>Which to thy Books redeem'd thee from the State:</l>
               <l>Our common Playes blush at thy Tragedy,</l>
               <l>The Law, and Life of Christian Poetry.</l>
               <l>For Action <hi>Joseph</hi> I would wish to be;</l>
               <l>For Writing, <hi>Grotius,</hi> I most honour thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>FRANK!</hi> Thou to us his Catechisme didst give,</l>
               <l>There Teaching, and here showing how to live.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sands</hi> in Christs Passion did before thee go</l>
               <l>In Tragick steps, which thou hast followed so,</l>
               <l>That were your Names conceal'd, it might be said,</l>
               <l>One did them both Translate, as One them made.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>S. <hi>GOTT.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:205034:11"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:205034:11"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:205034:12"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:205034:12"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:205034:13"/>
            <head>To his honoured Friend, <hi>FRANCIS GOLDSMITH,</hi> Esq; Ʋpon his Translation of, &amp;c.</head>
            <l>FRiend, did my fame and Muse shine forth as bright</l>
            <l>As the renowned <hi>Ben's,</hi> then would that light</l>
            <l>Like th' hour telling Sun, the Rectifier</l>
            <l>Of Clocks and Watches, shine to the whole quire</l>
            <l>Of common censu'rers, who would each correct</l>
            <l>His peccant humor by my Dialect.</l>
            <l>And their fond fancies pinning on my slieve,</l>
            <l>Without examination would believe:</l>
            <l>But since my humble Muse could never soar</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Parnassus</hi> height, nor is so popular</l>
            <l>To make all vote with me, let thy own worth,</l>
            <l>Thy well couch'd Phrase, neat lines, not tumbled forth</l>
            <l>By a Pye-corner Muse or wild sick braine,</l>
            <l>But the most noble issue of thy veine</l>
            <l>Speaks its own praise only, let these have grace,</l>
            <l>To stick like patches on a beauteous face.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho: Berney.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:205034:13"/>
            <head>In Sophompaneam, Tragaediam, a cultissimo viro, Domino <hi>Francisco Goldsmith,</hi> Anglico Idiomate donatam.</head>
            <l>DEtonat ignoto sublimis <hi>Grotius</hi> ore,</l>
            <l>Et maestam tragico syrmate verrit humum.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Josephum</hi> dederat Latio velamine tectum,</l>
            <l>Veste sub hàc nobis sed male notus erat.</l>
            <l>Musarum è sacra prodit <hi>faber aureus</hi> aulâ,</l>
            <l>Et scaenam egregiâ condidit arte novam.</l>
            <l>Sanctorum doctè huc transfert miracula patrum,</l>
            <l>Et nostri indigenas jam jubet esse soli.</l>
            <l>Quantus pro <hi>Phario</hi> dictabat jura Tyranno;</l>
            <l>Instantem{que} videns reppulit arte famem.</l>
            <l>En tantus <hi>Josephus</hi> adest, nosterque vocatus,</l>
            <l>Virtutisque tuae, clare vir, istud opus.</l>
            <l>Cum genio foelix, sic aurea carmina pangas,</l>
            <l>Sortitus merito es nomina digna tuo.</l>
            <l>Haec tibi cum <hi>Groti</hi> Elysias portentur ad oras,</l>
            <l>Gaudebis Latium dedicisse sonum.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>D. WHITFORD.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>—Debes etiam nobis Sophompaneam, pulchriori à te indutum tunicâ quàm olim fecerat illi indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentier parens, quam suam vellat Sandisius, &amp;, ni tibi foret injurius.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Tuissimus,</hi> Sandysius Staunton.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:205034:14"/>
            <p>THe History is recorded by <hi>Moses, Gen.</hi> 44. &amp; 45 Chapters, with the contexts there adjoyning: <hi>Psal.</hi> 105. <hi>Acts</hi> 7. by <hi>Philo</hi> in the life of <hi>Joseph;</hi> by <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sephus</hi> in his second book of the Jewish antiquities, and partly by <hi>Justin</hi> out of <hi>Trogus Pompeius</hi> the 36 Booke: It is extant also in <hi>Astapanus</hi> out of <hi>Alexander Polyhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stor,</hi> and in <hi>Demetrius:</hi> the places you may see in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sebius</hi> his preparation to the Gospel.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translators_preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:205034:14"/>
            <head>The Translators<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <p>This neither the Latin, nor Greek Tragick Writers use: But why may not they, as well as the Comick, commend the person of the Poet? or to win benevolence, and attention, expound the argument? <hi>Vossi. Instit. poeti. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 26.</p>
                  <p>Nor want I the example of <hi>Buchanan</hi> in his <hi>Jephthes, &amp; Baptistes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> PROLOGUE.</head>
            <l>HEre no <hi>Medea</hi> her own Children kils,</l>
            <l>Nor <hi>Hercules</hi> the Stage with horror fils:</l>
            <l>The Poet your delight and profit seeks,</l>
            <l>(Not borrowing a Fable from the Greeks;)</l>
            <l>But from the sacred Oracles of Truth,</l>
            <l>Where chaster then <hi>Hippolitus</hi> a Youth</l>
            <l>High Providence did out of Prison bring,</l>
            <l>To save and rule a Nation and a King.</l>
            <l>And after twenty yeers, who dead was thought,</l>
            <l>Is by his Sire and Brethren found unsought.</l>
            <l>If yet the Interpreter or Argument,</l>
            <l>Shall not to Criticks give a full content:</l>
            <l>Who look for sadder straines, and that we tread,</l>
            <l>More loftily in tragick buskins, read</l>
            <l>His <hi>Christus Patiens</hi> made yours by <hi>Sands,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Which to admire and love the World commands.</l>
            <l>But above all two Champions appear,</l>
            <l>The noble <hi>Falkland</hi> there, and <hi>Vossius</hi> here.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:205034:15"/>
            <list>
               <head>The Persons.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ioseph,</hi> who also is <hi>Sophompaneas.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chorus of Aethiopian Maides.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ramses</hi> Steward of <hi>Iosephs</hi> house.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iudah, Iosephs</hi> Brethren.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Reuben, Iosephs</hi> Brethren.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nuntius.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Simeon, Iosephs</hi> Brethren.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Benjamin, Iosephs</hi> Brethren.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> King of <hi>Egypt.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Mute Persons.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Manasses</hi> the Son of <hi>Ioseph.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The train and guard of <hi>Ioseph.</hi> Likewise of the King.</item>
               <item>Seven other Brethren of <hi>Ioseph.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The Scene, <hi>Memphis.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="act">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:205034:15"/>
            <head>The First Act. </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>JOSEPH.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hasing againe the Night his glorious head</l>
                  <l>The Sun shewes to the world, as from his bed</l>
                  <l>A Bridegroom rising comes in rich ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray</l>
                  <l>(1) Out of his chamber. The returning day</l>
                  <l>Doth by a constant course the Lord declare,</l>
                  <l>And of a Deity the Sun beames are</l>
                  <l>An evidence (2) where God we may behold,</l>
                  <l>Better then in all Ivory and Gold,</l>
                  <l>Inhabiting an Orbe of (3) mentall light.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hard labour too, and cares succeed the Night,</l>
                  <l>And of so vast a Kingdom all that space,</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Meroe</hi> to the shoar, all th' armes embrace</l>
                  <l>Of that great River, (4) whose head Heaven knowes,</l>
                  <l>On my sollicitous heart its burthen throwes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Some may admire the (5) beams from <hi>Libanus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The spotted marble, (6) Groves within my house,</l>
                  <l>Of artificiall meat so many dishes,</l>
                  <l>The severall kinds unknown to <hi>Nile</hi> of Fishes,</l>
                  <l>(7) Strange beasts from <hi>Africk,</hi> w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> yet want a name,</l>
                  <l>And birds which from the Arabian desart came,</l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:205034:16"/>
                  <l>(8) Wool from boughs by the <hi>Seres</hi> comb'd &amp; brought,</l>
                  <l>(9) At <hi>Babylon</hi> with skilffull needles wrought.</l>
                  <l>Bright (10) pearls a present from the Indian shoar,</l>
                  <l>The guards about my person and my door.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Vain, vain, these are, and for so great a weight</l>
                  <l>Too small a price. Under this diadems height</l>
                  <l>Lies a huge load of cares. In this attire,</l>
                  <l>To serve the King my office doth require,</l>
                  <l>And with such glittering lustre to surprize</l>
                  <l>The peoples mindes, whil'st it attracts their eyes;</l>
                  <l>This ornament I use, but not enjoy.</l>
                  <l>How much more freely liv'd I, when a boy;</l>
                  <l>Without such pensive thoughts I rul'd the Flock,</l>
                  <l>Which came from my great grandsire <hi>Abra'ms</hi> stock;</l>
                  <l>Where the sheep graze in <hi>Sichems</hi> pleasant grounds,</l>
                  <l>And whose fair vale a double hill surrounds.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>(11) Ambition did not a great table spread,</l>
                  <l>But the sweet (12) Mandrake with flowrs garnished</l>
                  <l>Gave me meat, &amp; the Palm, which, though with dates</l>
                  <l>Full laden, nothing of its height abates.</l>
                  <l>No sparkling wines of <hi>Meroe</hi> I knew,</l>
                  <l>No juice of barley which th' Egyptians brew,</l>
                  <l>And (13) <hi>Zythum</hi> call: but from the ground which burst</l>
                  <l>(14) A Wel quench'd mine and my forefathers thirst.</l>
                  <l>(15) My timbrell was a reed, but which did sing</l>
                  <l>To Syrian tunes the Worlds Almighty King.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If then, under my fathers eye, when none</l>
                  <l>Almost were, but my brethren, to me known;</l>
                  <l>Envy yet found me, and a dream, but late</l>
                  <l>Made true to me, could pull such cruel hate</l>
                  <l>On my innocent head, what may I look for now,</l>
                  <l>To whom a stranger all the Memphians bow?</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Egypt</hi> a rough Nation is, the yoak</l>
                  <l>Which of her native Lords hath often broke:</l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:205034:16"/>
                  <l>The harder is my task them to command,</l>
                  <l>With neither too remisse nor strict a hand.</l>
                  <l>But Mildnesse Gravity to her must joyn,</l>
                  <l>And Modesty with Majesty combine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet more. When a faire gale the sailes doth fill,</l>
                  <l>The meanest Master of a ship hath skill</l>
                  <l>To steer the course; but when from severall caves,</l>
                  <l>The rushing windes lash the tumultuous waves,</l>
                  <l>And lift up watry Mountaines from the deep,</l>
                  <l>Then through the stormy Seas the way to keep;</l>
                  <l>Ther's need of greatest art. <hi>Aegypt,</hi> thy boat,</l>
                  <l>In such a boysterous tempest seems to float.</l>
                  <l>Twice the beguiled Husbandman in vain,</l>
                  <l>Into a barren soil hath cast his grain.</l>
                  <l>From whence great danger to a State still growes,</l>
                  <l>For raging (16) hunger no alleagiance knows.</l>
                  <l>The People rather will rebell then sterve,</l>
                  <l>Almighty Father, who wouldst have me serve</l>
                  <l>Thy gracious providence, and that this Nation,</l>
                  <l>Unto my care should owe its preservation;</l>
                  <l>Most humble thanks and highest praise to thee</l>
                  <l>I give, by whom I things to come fore-see.</l>
                  <l>The former seven years plenty shall supply,</l>
                  <l>The seaven succeeding yeers great scarcity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nor by my gift doth <hi>Aegypt</hi> only live,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Syria</hi> doth likewise crave that I would give</l>
                  <l>Reliefe to her, that my old dreames now may</l>
                  <l>Prove waking truths, God hath found out this way.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hither by Famine driven twice unknown,</l>
                  <l>My brethren at my knees have fallen down.</l>
                  <l>Twice by them my old Sire, and who my dead</l>
                  <l>Mothers room fils, humbly incline their head.</l>
                  <l>I am that Star, to whom the Moon and Sun,</l>
                  <l>And the eleven Starrs have homage done.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:205034:17"/>
                  <l>Now though my brethrens hatred did devise</l>
                  <l>My death, though they of me made merchandise,</l>
                  <l>And to hard bondage sold; I have forgot</l>
                  <l>All this, and quite out of my mind it blot.</l>
                  <l>I know what 'tis to suffer, and am mild</l>
                  <l>By nature, so instructed from a child</l>
                  <l>By my good Father: yet lest in their breast</l>
                  <l>The dregs of an inveterate sin should rest</l>
                  <l>Not well purg'd out, I take a pious care;</l>
                  <l>And must use all my cunning to make bare</l>
                  <l>The secrets of the heart, which use to shroud</l>
                  <l>Themselves not seldome in too thick a cloud.</l>
                  <l>At dinner yesterday I to this end</l>
                  <l>The greatest Messe did to the youngest send;</l>
                  <l>That by their countenance I might divine,</l>
                  <l>Whether they lov'd the same whole blood with mine,</l>
                  <l>Or sparkes of ancient hate rak'd up did lie;</l>
                  <l>Nor know I yet: I must them further try.</l>
                  <l>(17) Ile charge the Lad that he my cup did steale,</l>
                  <l>How they affect him, this will best reveale.</l>
                  <l>A vessell doth not alwaies plough the seas</l>
                  <l>In a straight line; but for the Pilots ease</l>
                  <l>And better speed it often doth availe,</l>
                  <l>To fetch a compasse with an oblique saile.</l>
                  <l>Truth by a wile is sometimes understood;</l>
                  <l>I hope, to finde; if not, to make them good.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hear me <hi>Manasses,</hi> when a man thou art,</l>
                  <l>And of this Realm hereafter any part</l>
                  <l>Fall to thy Government, let Aegypt be</l>
                  <l>Thy Countrey, she hath well deserv'd so. See,</l>
                  <l>Her benefits thou recompence. The King</l>
                  <l>Next unto God think the most sacred thing.</l>
                  <l>Let the supream Law be him to obey,</l>
                  <l>And tribute of a loyall heart to pay;</l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:205034:17"/>
                  <l>Then pride the tumour of the mind keep down,</l>
                  <l>(18) Power is but frail, a King that smiles may frown.</l>
                  <l>A sudden change hath in an hour laid flat</l>
                  <l>Him on the ground, who above Princes sat;</l>
                  <l>And often but a little space between</l>
                  <l>A pallace and a dungeon is seen.</l>
                  <l>If any wrong be done thee, if a wound</l>
                  <l>Thine honour shall receive, be ever found</l>
                  <l>Ready to pardon. To offend how prone</l>
                  <l>We are, by our first parents fall is known,</l>
                  <l>Whose hand did the forbidden apple pull.</l>
                  <l>To them that mercy shew, God's mercifull:</l>
                  <l>By their own law, and with what measure they</l>
                  <l>Shall deal, he will to every man repay.</l>
                  <l>The soveraign virtue &amp; (19) which keeps in breath</l>
                  <l>All virtues, and doth triumph over death,</l>
                  <l>Is Piety. Idlenesse alwaies fly,</l>
                  <l>The friend to vice, Honor her selfe beares high.</l>
                  <l>For when the world in her illustrious seat,</l>
                  <l>Shall gaze on thee, thy fame must needs be great;</l>
                  <l>But whether good or bad this in thee lies.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now go we to survey the Granaries,</l>
                  <l>Her store where this great City doth reserve,</l>
                  <l>Lest from my charge in any part I swerve.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>(20) <hi>Chorus.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN a rich bed, her Lord gone thence,</l>
                  <l>With his Propheticke eloquence,</l>
                  <l>(21) <hi>Asenath</hi> wearied lies, the day</l>
                  <l>The losses of the night must pay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here that no noise disturbe her sleep,</l>
                  <l>By her command the doors we keep,</l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:205034:18"/>
                  <l>To wait on her sent (by our King,</l>
                  <l>Whose royall blood (22) from <hi>Cush</hi> doth spring)</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Nubae</hi>'s utmost parts, through whose</l>
                  <l>Dry land the River <hi>Niger</hi> flowes.</l>
                  <l>Our hair in circling waves doth run,</l>
                  <l>Not curl'd with Irons, but the Sun.</l>
                  <l>(23) With noses flat and skin like jeat,</l>
                  <l>Made black by too contiguous heat;</l>
                  <l>Thick are our lips where fenced lie,</l>
                  <l>Our teeth as white as ivory.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O happy house, which govern'd art</l>
                  <l>By a chast couple with one heart.</l>
                  <l>The Children like the Father, known</l>
                  <l>Are by their looks to be his own:</l>
                  <l>Which makes the vertuous mother glad;</l>
                  <l>Nor doth her Lord, after the bad</l>
                  <l>(24) Custome of barbarous Princes range,</l>
                  <l>Who every night their wives do change;</l>
                  <l>Whereby is strife and hatred sown,</l>
                  <l>But he delights in her alone:</l>
                  <l>And in his honest brest no room</l>
                  <l>Is for strange fires; to overcome</l>
                  <l>Which, he did know long since, when he,</l>
                  <l>Though but a servant, yet more free</l>
                  <l>Then his vile mistris, did despise</l>
                  <l>The glance of her adulterous eyes.</l>
                  <l>With naked brests and wanton speech,</l>
                  <l>Who might command, did first beseech;</l>
                  <l>Then threaten, but against a rock,</l>
                  <l>In vain the foaming billowes knock.</l>
                  <l>Would you, saith he, have me no lesse</l>
                  <l>Commit, then threefold wickednesse.</l>
                  <l>Madam, should I dishonour you,</l>
                  <l>And to my Lord prove most untrue;</l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:205034:18"/>
                  <l>Breaking the trust he puts me in,</l>
                  <l>And against God should I thus sin?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O thou, who guid'st the starry sphear,</l>
                  <l>Ordering the Seasons of the Year:</l>
                  <l>The spring with Roses thou dost crown,</l>
                  <l>In Summers heat corn ripe is grown.</l>
                  <l>Then Autumne purple grapes brings forth,</l>
                  <l>Then comes cold winter from the North.</l>
                  <l>(25) How stands it with thy providence,</l>
                  <l>That Vice should tread on Innocence?</l>
                  <l>A woman who with lust did burn,</l>
                  <l>Which, when repuls'd, to rage did turn,</l>
                  <l>His garment a false evidence,</l>
                  <l>Keeps in her hand, that she from thence</l>
                  <l>Her husband might delude, and lay</l>
                  <l>The crime on him who fled away.</l>
                  <l>The Judge corrupting with a kisse,</l>
                  <l>But he to whom chastity is</l>
                  <l>A treble guard, and (26) rarely known</l>
                  <l>To Beauty a companion,</l>
                  <l>Into a cruell dungeon cast,</l>
                  <l>With true adulterers lies fast.</l>
                  <l>Yet even there how foul the breach.</l>
                  <l>Of wedlock is, he doth them teach.</l>
                  <l>The Prisoners wonder in so young</l>
                  <l>A head, to hear so grave a toung,</l>
                  <l>Whose honest looks and modest eyes,</l>
                  <l>With reverent awe did them surprise.</l>
                  <l>Among his fellow prisoners he,</l>
                  <l>Is made a Judge; and when they see</l>
                  <l>What life he leads, and by it try</l>
                  <l>Their own, they all do guilty cry,</l>
                  <l>God neither doth quite hide his way</l>
                  <l>From us, nor yet it quite display.</l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:205034:19"/>
                  <l>His Children he keeps in a state</l>
                  <l>Not wanton, not too delicate.</l>
                  <l>As a good Captaine doth enure,</l>
                  <l>His Souldiers hardship to endure:</l>
                  <l>So the great Father of us all,</l>
                  <l>Whom he doth love, will have to fall</l>
                  <l>Into affliction, lest the Soul</l>
                  <l>Through ease, should grow corrupt and foul.</l>
                  <l>Yet leaves he not them comfortlesse,</l>
                  <l>But in the midst of their distresse</l>
                  <l>Courage unto his own doth give,</l>
                  <l>(27) Who with glad hopes in patience live.</l>
                  <l>In a dark dungeon and cold chaines,</l>
                  <l>Our Lord his freedom still retaines;</l>
                  <l>And did keepe others, who elsewhere</l>
                  <l>Resisted lust, here conquers fear.</l>
                  <l>Whose beauty did his Mistrisse take,</l>
                  <l>His virtue did the captive make</l>
                  <l>And Keeper love him. To his care</l>
                  <l>The wretched rabble trusted are.</l>
                  <l>Hence he presag'd what happen'd since,</l>
                  <l>And in a Prison was a Prince.</l>
                  <l>Where scarce the Sun did ever shine,</l>
                  <l>Thither did come a light divine,</l>
                  <l>Fixing in his pure heart its beames,</l>
                  <l>Interpreting the prisoners dreames:</l>
                  <l>Pardon to one, death he foretels</l>
                  <l>To th' other. In his voice God dwels.</l>
                  <l>Thus flow'd adversities rough stream,</l>
                  <l>(28) Till the King troubled with a dream,</l>
                  <l>In vain did the (29) Magicians call,</l>
                  <l>In vain, what new fate should befall</l>
                  <l>Among (30) Heavens constellations sought:</l>
                  <l>The Prophet then from bonds was brought,</l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:205034:19"/>
                  <l>Worthier a chaine of gold and ring,</l>
                  <l>(31) A silk white robe, &amp; next the King</l>
                  <l>To rule the Land, then whom alone</l>
                  <l>He lower now sits in the Throne.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="act">
            <head>The second Act.</head>
            <stage>Ramses, Judah, Reuben.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ram.</speaker>
               <l>YOuth, to thy years my pitty I afford,</l>
               <l>Who must go backe a prisoner to my Lord,</l>
               <l>Great (1) <hi>Sophompaneas.</hi> But what he commands,</l>
               <l>Our duty must perform, A servant stands</l>
               <l>Not to controule his master, but obay.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jud.</speaker>
               <l>Yet, <hi>Ramses,</hi> hear me a few words I pray:</l>
               <l>If his ingenuous face may not acquit</l>
               <l>Him from such guilt, and tender age scarce fit</l>
               <l>For any fraud, what yesterday we did,</l>
               <l>Weigh now. Our money by your error hid</l>
               <l>In our sacks, of our own accord again</l>
               <l>We brought from <hi>Syria,</hi> where none could complain,</l>
               <l>Or challenge it: a present we did adde,</l>
               <l>Though small, such as we in our Country had.</l>
               <l>A soveraign salve for wounds (2) the precious Balme,</l>
               <l>(3) Dates like mens fingers growing on the Palme.</l>
               <l>(4) Spices, Nuts, Almonds, (5) Nectar of the Bees,</l>
               <l>Sweet smelling Myrrh, w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> drops from weeping trees.</l>
               <l>More could our beasts have born, you must confess,</l>
               <l>We were not covetous, but thieves much less.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ram.</speaker>
               <l>Words, which the fact confutes, are spent in vain,</l>
               <l>I do not charge you, that you had a gain:</l>
               <l>Your money in your sacks, we have no lack</l>
               <l>Of mony. But the Cup found in this sack</l>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:205034:20"/>
               <l>Is that wherein my Lord doth offer wine,</l>
               <l>When he poures out his prayers and (6) would divine.</l>
               <l>For the great God of Heaven doth often make,</l>
               <l>Him of his secret councels to partake.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l>If he know secrets, he can also tell,</l>
               <l>That we are innocent.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ram.</speaker>
               <l>Your bosomes well</l>
               <l>Examine. Better none then thy own heart</l>
               <l>Will speak the truth. But take heed lest in part</l>
               <l>Thou judge thy selfe: thou must into the track,</l>
               <l>And whole course of thy former life look back.</l>
               <l>God slow to wrath, to punish is not wont</l>
               <l>At first, but when heaps of new sins do mount</l>
               <l>Upon the old (7) his arm which was so flow</l>
               <l>In lifting up fals with the heavyer blow.</l>
               <l>The Giants in old time liv'd long undrown'd,</l>
               <l>Before that Heaven did earth and seas confound.</l>
               <l>When on the Mountain tops the waves did roar,</l>
               <l>And made the World a sea without a shoar.</l>
               <l>Proud <hi>Babel</hi> threatning heaven was built high,</l>
               <l>Ere unknown tongues dash'd the conspiracy.</l>
               <l>Long in unnaturall lusts had <hi>Sodom</hi> laine,</l>
               <l>Ere God sulphureous showres of fire did rain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jud.</speaker>
               <l>O <hi>Dothan</hi> dismall name! O horrid pit,</l>
               <l>And thou Arabian greedy Merchant fit</l>
               <l>For any purchase, how you now perplex</l>
               <l>My sad rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbrance and my conscience vex!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reub.</speaker>
               <l>Spake I not oft to you, not to commit</l>
               <l>Such wickedness? His ruthfull looks are yet</l>
               <l>Fresh in my minde, when he besought with teares</l>
               <l>His brethren; at his cry who stopt their ears:</l>
               <l>But Heaven hath heard him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jud.</speaker>
               <l>You may eas'ly blame</l>
               <l>Anothers fault, though guilty of the same.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ram.</speaker>
               <l>Among your selves what do you mutter thus?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jud.</speaker>
               <l>To think on <hi>Syria</hi> it doth trouble us,</l>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:205034:20"/>
               <l>Our Countrey, where our Ancestors did live,</l>
               <l>Famous for goodnesse, to whom Kings did give</l>
               <l>The hand of Friendship, and them faithfull found,</l>
               <l>Who were for hospitality renown'd,</l>
               <l>Whose good report through all the Region flies,</l>
               <l>Which between <hi>Jordan</hi> and <hi>Euphrates</hi> lies.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ram.</speaker>
               <l>Posterity not alwaies doth inherit</l>
               <l>The praises of their Ancestors high merit;</l>
               <l>But 'tis oft seen, that a degenerate race,</l>
               <l>With lust and falsehood doth the stock disgrace.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jud.</speaker>
               <l>O child, and of our blood a part,</l>
               <l>Which in thy youths fresh flower art,</l>
               <l>Wherein doth this poor comfort lie,</l>
               <l>Thou know'st not thine own misery.</l>
               <l>O gracefull visage, blushing sweet,</l>
               <l>As when with purple milk doth meet;</l>
               <l>Or the first dawning of the rose,</l>
               <l>Its beauty in the bud disclose.</l>
               <l>And thou, like Lybian gold, ô hair,</l>
               <l>The pastime of the wanton air:</l>
               <l>What dire blow shall unto thee give</l>
               <l>Thy death, or if thou chance to live,</l>
               <l>What horrid dungeon shall thee hold?</l>
               <l>Or in what land shalt thou be sold,</l>
               <l>Far from us, and thy Father, where</l>
               <l>A servile yoak thy neck shall bear?</l>
               <l>Alas born unto better sates,</l>
               <l>Whose Ancestors were Princes mates.</l>
               <l>In thy gay coat thy Father thee</l>
               <l>Playing about no more shall see.</l>
               <l>Nor when at high noon the Suns heat</l>
               <l>Shall make us from our Flocks retreat,</l>
               <l>(Under a tree, or by a spring)</l>
               <l>Shalt thou in hast our dinner bring.</l>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:205034:21"/>
               <l>And some perhaps (for spite doth raigne</l>
               <l>In every Country) will againe</l>
               <l>Accuse thee falsely, when that thee</l>
               <l>A stranger, poor, forlorn they see.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ram.</speaker>
               <l>To love him you do well, who is so nigh</l>
               <l>In bloud. (8) Among men great diversity</l>
               <l>There is of manners, and in every land</l>
               <l>Are severall laws, as the Prince wil command,</l>
               <l>Or people make for publike benefit:</l>
               <l>(9) This law is every where, nor is it writ</l>
               <l>In Cedar tables, nor in Marble cut;</l>
               <l>Nor brasse, but (10) in the heart God hath it put.</l>
               <l>Who flies it, flies himselfe: Wild beasts we find,</l>
               <l>To love by nature those of their own kind.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jud.</speaker>
               <l>Our very griefe you touch, as nothing more.</l>
               <l>But see where strongly guarded to his door</l>
               <l>The Governor is comming, if we now</l>
               <l>Not guilty plead, who will believe us? How,</l>
               <l>If we confesse, can we for pardon pray?</l>
               <l>Oh I am at a losse <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> what I should say,</l>
               <l>Or how to look I know not. Conscience</l>
               <l>Of my old guilt takes from me all defence.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Ramses, Joseph, Judah.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ram.</speaker>
               <l>The thiefe is taken, the cup safe, we found</l>
               <l>It with this Lad, whom we have brought here bound.</l>
               <l>His brethren uncompel'd would with him go,</l>
               <l>Rending their garments to expresse their woe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jos.</speaker>
               <l>What wretched avarice, what boldnesse drave</l>
               <l>You to this deed? Wot you not that I have</l>
               <l>Intelligence from heaven, that God a mind</l>
               <l>Hath given me, which all hid things can find:</l>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:205034:21"/>
               <l>And, which another Prophet is to me</l>
               <l>Wisdome, whose clear eyes in the dark can see?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jud.</speaker>
               <l>Right high and mighty Prince, the second head</l>
               <l>Of this great Kingdom, at whose feet we spread</l>
               <l>Our hands, what can we say? how shall we cleer</l>
               <l>Our selves, against whom God doth thus appear?</l>
               <l>But thou who Nations rul'st, rule what is more,</l>
               <l>Thy wrath, nor let thy will be as thy pow'r.</l>
               <l>Make thy gift good: our lives by thee we have</l>
               <l>Preserv'd from famine, now again us save.</l>
               <l>(11) Mercy alone man nigh to God doth make,</l>
               <l>Us and our brother for thy bond-men take.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jos.</speaker>
               <l>(12) Such hath bin, and such is the custome still</l>
               <l>Of many Eastern Nations, that they will</l>
               <l>Not that the punishment should have an end</l>
               <l>In them who are found guilty, but extend</l>
               <l>To parents, children, brethren, crimes of one</l>
               <l>(13) Five families wrap in like contagion.</l>
               <l>Whil'st I in <hi>Aegypt</hi> do bear any sway,</l>
               <l>Heer's no such law, nor after me, I pray,</l>
               <l>May any such be. He who sins shall bear</l>
               <l>His sin himself: no further shall the fear</l>
               <l>Go then the fault, or to the heir descend.</l>
               <l>He shall my bond-slave be that did offend;</l>
               <l>With whom the Cup was found, I will release</l>
               <l>The rest, unto your Sire go home in peace.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jud.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Though our condition and your excellence</l>
                  <l>Make me afraid unto so great a Prince</l>
                  <l>To speak, yet I beseech you to suspend</l>
                  <l>Your anger, and a gracious ear to lend</l>
                  <l>Unto a poor distressed Syrian,</l>
                  <l>But what for audience is enough, a man.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When hither first the Famine did us drive,</l>
                  <l>You did us aske, we answered, that alive</l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:205034:22"/>
                  <l>We had a Father, but exceeding old;</l>
                  <l>Who had above twice threescore winters told.</l>
                  <l>And that besides us ten he had a boy,</l>
                  <l>A little one, his comfort and his joy;</l>
                  <l>As born in his old age, and of his mother</l>
                  <l>The only issue left, his elder brother</l>
                  <l>Whom the same wombe did bear is long since dead.</l>
                  <l>This child to you that we should hither lead</l>
                  <l>Him with your Princely favours to enrich,</l>
                  <l>A strict command you did us give. To which</l>
                  <l>It nothing could availe us to reply:</l>
                  <l>Our Father, if the lad him leave, will die.</l>
                  <l>You said, that we no more should have access</l>
                  <l>Unto you, or behold your face, unless</l>
                  <l>Our Brother came; which when the old man heard,</l>
                  <l>His reverend face with ashes he besmear'd,</l>
                  <l>And silent sate and wept. When all our food</l>
                  <l>Began to fail us, and we fearfull stood</l>
                  <l>Looking on one another at the nigh</l>
                  <l>Approaching famine; Go, said he, and buy</l>
                  <l>More corn for us in <hi>Aegypt.</hi> We contend,</l>
                  <l>That you must be obey'd: if he not send</l>
                  <l>Our youngest brother with us, but at home</l>
                  <l>Him keep, we doubtless back should empty come.</l>
                  <l>But sadly he: two children did my dear,</l>
                  <l>My best beloved <hi>Rachel</hi> to me bear:</l>
                  <l>The first of them whom I shall ne'r see more,</l>
                  <l>A wild beast (so yee told me) did devoure.</l>
                  <l>If now you take this other from my sight,</l>
                  <l>And any mischiefe should upon him light,</l>
                  <l>(As our fraile lives to many dangers still</l>
                  <l>Exposed are) then think I pray what will</l>
                  <l>Become of my gray hairs: with griefe and woe</l>
                  <l>Consum'd I down into the grave shall go.</l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:205034:22"/>
                  <l>Now I beseech you even for the sake</l>
                  <l>Of this old man, (your self if I may make</l>
                  <l>So bold, had once a father) and to save</l>
                  <l>His life, which if he miss the Lad will have</l>
                  <l>A speedy period, do not suffer it</l>
                  <l>Among your glorious titles to be writ,</l>
                  <l>Great Saviour of <hi>Aegypt:</hi> You did slay</l>
                  <l>An old man. In my brothers stead, I pray,</l>
                  <l>Take me. I can do better service. He</l>
                  <l>A weak and tender child will rather be</l>
                  <l>A burden to a house. I did become</l>
                  <l>A surety for him to my Father, whom</l>
                  <l>O let me never see, unless I keep</l>
                  <l>My promise, lest he me accuse and weep,</l>
                  <l>Till life dissolve, and when in earths dark vault</l>
                  <l>I bury him, I bury there my fault.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jos.</speaker>
               <l>Not all which you have said, though something, I</l>
               <l>Beleeve. Who doth a matter hastily</l>
               <l>Determine, he unto repentance hies</l>
               <l>The ready way. I further will advise.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jud.</speaker>
               <l>If dead, ô happy <hi>Joseph</hi> then, that thou</l>
               <l>These miseries dost not feel with us now;</l>
               <l>If living, that God unto whom belongs</l>
               <l>Vengeance not unreveng'd doth see thy wrongs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
               <l>VVHere <hi>Aegypt</hi> when the Sun doth rise</l>
               <l>Looks on his beams (14) <hi>Phoenicia</hi> lies;</l>
               <l>Which, whether it more good or ill</l>
               <l>Hath done to mankind may be still</l>
               <l>A question. For inventions rare,</l>
               <l>(15) <hi>Taauta</hi> doth the praises bear.</l>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:205034:23"/>
               <l>(16) In twice twelve letters to comprize,</l>
               <l>Which first did teach what in the skies,</l>
               <l>Or sea, or land, or in the mind</l>
               <l>Of man (which all containes) we find.</l>
               <l>But as if sicknesse, beasts of prey,</l>
               <l>Not fast enough snatch men away.</l>
               <l>And, which among the Reeds of <hi>Nile,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In ambush lies the (17) Crocodile,</l>
               <l>The same (18) to death a new way shows</l>
               <l>In a frail Bark the sea which plows.</l>
               <l>As formerly in sight oth' shore,</l>
               <l>The vessell now sailes by no more:</l>
               <l>But lanching out into the deep</l>
               <l>Mediterranean Sea, doth keep</l>
               <l>Now Southward, then the Northern Star</l>
               <l>It follows: not to fetch from far</l>
               <l>What may give nature fresh supplies,</l>
               <l>Whose use a few things do suffice.</l>
               <l>But (19) purple, by Kings to be worn,</l>
               <l>And the rich fingers to adorn;</l>
               <l>The (20) Emerald then grasse more green,</l>
               <l>Which sparkling in the ring is seen.</l>
               <l>This did the thirst of gold devise,</l>
               <l>Mad thirst of gold, which to despise</l>
               <l>The raging of the sea, the wrath</l>
               <l>Of Heaven, and (21) to a thin plank hath</l>
               <l>Our precious lives taught to commit.</l>
               <l>Dire avarice, to what crimes doth it</l>
               <l>Not drive adventurous mankind? Hence,</l>
               <l>Of right or wrong no difference</l>
               <l>Is made: no place, no persons are</l>
               <l>From rapine safe, nor will men spare</l>
               <l>The very Altars; but to meet</l>
               <l>With plunder any where is sweet.</l>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:205034:23"/>
               <l>(22) O happy the first age, in which</l>
               <l>He who found Strawberries was rich;</l>
               <l>Or tasted the delicious juice,</l>
               <l>Which trees unplanted did produce.</l>
               <l>One Law there was, Vice not to know:</l>
               <l>(33) A simple life, chast enough, though</l>
               <l>Naked. But when (24) a coat became</l>
               <l>A covering to hide our shame;</l>
               <l>And then by violence the field</l>
               <l>A crop of corn was forc'd to yeeld,</l>
               <l>The Brother did his hands imbrew,</l>
               <l>In's Brothers blood, and anger knew</l>
               <l>No kindred. Nor did the bold hand</l>
               <l>Of men stay here: the trembling land</l>
               <l>Her bowels to be digg'd did feel,</l>
               <l>And better hid, a veine of steel</l>
               <l>Was found. Sterne slaughter further goes,</l>
               <l>Than single bodies; the sword mowes</l>
               <l>Great Nations in a short space,</l>
               <l>And powerfull wickednesse the face</l>
               <l>Of glorious war so long did wear,</l>
               <l>Till the earth could no longer bear,</l>
               <l>But to her aid the Sea did call,</l>
               <l>Another Sea from Heaven did fall.</l>
               <l>(25) With such a noise, as <hi>Nile</hi> down flows,</l>
               <l>When from steep Rocks himself he throws.</l>
               <l>But neither hath it for the good</l>
               <l>Of mankind bin to presse the blood</l>
               <l>Of grapes: by wine great dammage came,</l>
               <l>(26) The son laught at his fathers shame;</l>
               <l>(27) The daughter to her Father brought</l>
               <l>A Grandchilde, what hath lust not wrought?</l>
               <l>O <hi>Aegypt,</hi> thee and these our times</l>
               <l>We much congratulate, whose crimes</l>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:205034:24"/>
               <l>An excellent Governour restraines,</l>
               <l>And in the narrowest bounds containes.</l>
               <l>Who vice by laws makes men give o're,</l>
               <l>But by his own example more.</l>
               <l>Stay here; a tempest up is rais'd: now wee</l>
               <l>How it at length will be appeas'd, would see.</l>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="act">
            <head>The third Act.</head>
            <stage>Nuntius, Joseph.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nun.</speaker>
               <l>ALL that fierce people bordering on the (1) red,</l>
               <l>And the Carpathian Sea, by fury led</l>
               <l>Are up in armes. Each man is his own law,</l>
               <l>And the great Kings command keeps none in awe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jos.</speaker>
               <l>A crime in <hi>Aegypt</hi> frequent now, though great.</l>
               <l>But it is not enough to know what heat</l>
               <l>A pestilence doth rage with, or what part</l>
               <l>It hath infected, and where lies the smart.</l>
               <l>Who a disease would cure the cause must know;</l>
               <l>Say, from what fountain did this mischiefe flow?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nun.</speaker>
               <l>The Magistrates gave the first cause, whil'st they</l>
               <l>Greedy of gain your orders disobey;</l>
               <l>And at excessive rates the corn transport,</l>
               <l>Whereby the Country dweller had but short</l>
               <l>Allowance: and still less and less. Some sterve;</l>
               <l>The wealthy buyer longer did preserve</l>
               <l>His life; (2) bread by a griping hand was sold:</l>
               <l>So much more great the hunger was of gold.</l>
               <l>When no more corn could in the fields be found,</l>
               <l>The people then the cattell and the ground</l>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:205034:24"/>
               <l>Began to envy, and their bellies fill</l>
               <l>With shrubs and herbs: nor therein saw what ill</l>
               <l>They did. For when the earth of grass was void,</l>
               <l>The Flocks and Herds by famine were destroy'd;</l>
               <l>And all which nature gives for food to men.</l>
               <l>On Dogs the Country sentinels they then,</l>
               <l>Yea, on the (3) sacred Ibis, and on such</l>
               <l>Unclean things too, as loathsome are to touch,</l>
               <l>A feast make. Who would think it? (4) Asps are meat</l>
               <l>To some, and wittingly they poyson eat.</l>
               <l>Their cheeks are gastly pale, loose hangs their skin,</l>
               <l>With joynts wide gaping, eyes deep sunk within.</l>
               <l>Sad sighing did a while complaints suppress;</l>
               <l>At length some wont in sloth and idleness</l>
               <l>To spend their daies, who formerly durst prate,</l>
               <l>And dart ill language at the Magistrate,</l>
               <l>Call Conventicles, (5) when the shady Night</l>
               <l>Destroyes all colours, and obscures the Light:</l>
               <l>Adding new faults; or when (as miseries</l>
               <l>Make men devout) to offer sacrifice</l>
               <l>The people met, there they with speeches take</l>
               <l>The multitude. What end will this dearth make?</l>
               <l>Or what hope is there left for us? they say,</l>
               <l>Is it for this our patience doth stay,</l>
               <l>That we may fight who shall have the first bit</l>
               <l>Of th' others limbs, that on the Fathers spit</l>
               <l>The sor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> roasted, and (6) the mother bear</l>
               <l>Her ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>? Do ye now stand in fear</l>
               <l>Of Soveraigne power? this is nothing, but</l>
               <l>An empty name, which in a fright may put</l>
               <l>Those who walk by themselves, but he who shall</l>
               <l>Awe single persons is afraid of all.</l>
               <l>These things once heard, every one as he goes</l>
               <l>Doth scatter, and enlarge. A few, but whose</l>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:205034:25"/>
               <l>Authority was over-rul'd, contend,</l>
               <l>That they to you should a Petition send.</l>
               <l>The greater part, as if an hornet had</l>
               <l>Them stung, then their first setters on more mad</l>
               <l>Doth rage. With what a violence the wind</l>
               <l>Breaking the Mountain where it was confin'd,</l>
               <l>And rushing through the empty air down casts</l>
               <l>The sturdy oakes: with such a fury hasts</l>
               <l>The Country rout, and stones and fire-burnt stakes,</l>
               <l>And pieces of a broken plow up takes.</l>
               <l>A thousand voices cry: to (7) <hi>Coptos</hi> where</l>
               <l>The higher power sit; we may have there</l>
               <l>Bread and revenge. The army greater grows</l>
               <l>In marching. Many, as along it goes,</l>
               <l>Admire and make the number: when they came</l>
               <l>Nigh to the town, the gates they on a flame</l>
               <l>With torches set. The timber fire soon takes,</l>
               <l>And a strong Eastern wind it fiercermakes;</l>
               <l>And drives to the next houses: the sparkes fly:</l>
               <l>A globe of pitchy smoak ascends the skie.</l>
               <l>And whil'st the frighted Citizens prepare</l>
               <l>To quench the flame, the Pesants of this fear</l>
               <l>Taking advantage, where the wall was thin,</l>
               <l>And weakly guarded, on that side break in.</l>
               <l>And forthwith from the Magazines they take,</l>
               <l>And put on armes, and glittering weapons shake.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jos.</speaker>
               <l>Doth at the Magistrate this only strike?</l>
               <l>Or doth it wander further, and alike</l>
               <l>Involve the guilty and the innocent?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nun.</speaker>
               <l>The rage at first against the Rulers bent</l>
               <l>Hath many cut in pieces: for the Grave</l>
               <l>Nothing was left of them. A few did save</l>
               <l>Themselves by flight, whom now a secret den</l>
               <l>Of a wild beast doth hide. The garners then</l>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:205034:25"/>
               <l>They fall upon. The corn, (which, if a right,</l>
               <l>And equall dole had bin, a long while might</l>
               <l>Have driven back the famine) snatcht away</l>
               <l>Without all rule and measure, a short stay</l>
               <l>Thereof did make. The mischiefe thus begun,</l>
               <l>Like an incurable disease did run.</l>
               <l>And whatsoere the publike treasury,</l>
               <l>Or private coffers kept, what gifts on high</l>
               <l>Hang in the temples, all a prey became:</l>
               <l>The greedy hand not put back by the flame</l>
               <l>Doth plunder burning <hi>Coptos.</hi> Then their hate</l>
               <l>Both Noble men and youths doth captivate,</l>
               <l>Who to a barbarous soile for slaves are sold.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jos.</speaker>
               <l>To buy a free-borne race who was so bold?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nun.</speaker>
               <l>The twelve Arabian Princes, <hi>Ismaels</hi> seed.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jos.</speaker>
               <l>That Nation is of <hi>Hagar</hi> the right breed,</l>
               <l>Like her, in unjust manners. But, say, how</l>
               <l>The City being tane is govern'd now.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nun.</speaker>
               <l>Not any form held long: they first chose one</l>
               <l>With soveraigne power; him they dislike anon.</l>
               <l>Another is set up by armes, but whose</l>
               <l>Authority is limited by those</l>
               <l>That are joyn'd fellows with him: nor did this</l>
               <l>Continue long: the government then is</l>
               <l>Committed to the people. Clamour there</l>
               <l>Carries all votes, and boldness sway doth bear.</l>
               <l>Nor is their raging discord within bounds</l>
               <l>Of words contain'd: the matter's tri'd by wounds.</l>
               <l>Their swords to mutuall slaughter then they draw,</l>
               <l>Ingag'd in a sharp conflict I them saw.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jos.</speaker>
               <l>These tidings promise present victory.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ramses,</hi> what troops you can, raise speedily</l>
               <l>To compasse in the City. Ile convey</l>
               <l>Men under ground, who by a secret way</l>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:205034:26"/>
               <l>Shall come within the wals: and you shall have</l>
               <l>(8) The battering Ram, and (9) creeping Vine to save</l>
               <l>Your heads in the assault. When thus you shall</l>
               <l>Enjoy the town, let not the Souldier fall</l>
               <l>To kill or spoil the Citizens. From me</l>
               <l>Let him expect reward; the King will be</l>
               <l>Able to pay them all: ô let none then</l>
               <l>Seek gain by ruin of his Countrymen.</l>
               <l>The civill government give not to such</l>
               <l>As over wealthy be, who having much</l>
               <l>Still covet more, and will no liberty</l>
               <l>Allow the people, or themselves deny:</l>
               <l>Nor yet to beggers; envy feeds upon</l>
               <l>The hearts of such, which an obstruction</l>
               <l>To justice is, foe to society,</l>
               <l>On others good casting an evill eie.</l>
               <l>The middle sort will govern best, who be</l>
               <l>From ryot far, from sordid basenesse free.</l>
               <l>Corn I will send from hence, which through the land</l>
               <l>You may distribute with an equall hand.</l>
               <l>Where th'utmost Pharian border lies, which o're</l>
               <l>The Red Sea hath a prospect to the shore</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> with strong towers those parts defend.</l>
               <l>Propitious Heaven better times will send,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Aegypt</hi> shall those (10) Nabataeans tame,</l>
               <l>Which warme themselves in our afflictions flame.</l>
               <l>Them, who their power abus'd, commit to close,</l>
               <l>And dark imprisonment, and likewise those,</l>
               <l>Who, though of wicked Magistrates, the blood</l>
               <l>Have fouly spilt; the manner is not good,</l>
               <l>Nor tolerable, and a foe to peace,</l>
               <l>Those punishments more terror will encrease,</l>
               <l>Which not in hasty wrath inflicted bee,</l>
               <l>But by, grave councels friend, a slow decree.</l>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:205034:26"/>
               <l>Let them a pardon find, who did transgresse</l>
               <l>No more, then hunger thereunto did press;</l>
               <l>Nor with a covetous mind the wealth invade</l>
               <l>Of others. But who of their fellows made</l>
               <l>A mock and gain, what Laws they did invent,</l>
               <l>Let them now feel in their own punishment.</l>
               <l>(11) Alive them bury in the Mines: there they</l>
               <l>By labour measuring time, depriv'd of day,</l>
               <l>Shall heavy shackles at their heels draw still.</l>
               <l>But yet let these be fed too: and what ill</l>
               <l>Unto their Country by their dire offence</l>
               <l>Is done, let their example recompence.</l>
               <l>And their long miseries to others be</l>
               <l>A wholesome spectacle. For these things, see</l>
               <l>Thou care. Now what concerns my own estate,</l>
               <l>(12) Ile to my faithfull Wife within relate.</l>
               <stage>Judah, Simeon.</stage>
               <l>O <hi>Simeon,</hi> what a man is this! How he</l>
               <l>Hath all things wisely done! How equall bee</l>
               <l>His censures to the merits of the cause,</l>
               <l>How close he keeps to justice and the Laws!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <l>Such I have long observ'd him, having been</l>
               <l>A pledge here for you. I have often seen</l>
               <l>Him sit, and (13) with an equall patience hear</l>
               <l>Both sides: nor could it by his words appear;</l>
               <l>Nor by his looks or gesture any signe</l>
               <l>Could I discover, how he did incline:</l>
               <l>The credit of the witnesses prevail'd</l>
               <l>More then the number with him: If there fail'd</l>
               <l>A witnesse, then the life which formerly</l>
               <l>The prisoner led, did that defect supply.</l>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:205034:27"/>
               <l>To follow the strict rules of Law he sought,</l>
               <l>Unlesse where clemency perswaded ought</l>
               <l>To bate of rigour, yet not so unbent,</l>
               <l>As vice from thence should take encouragement:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jud.</speaker>
               <l>What should I say, that <hi>Sophompaneas</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yesterday feasting us did each guest place</l>
               <l>According to our birth by nature.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <l>This,</l>
               <l>Beleeve me Brother, but the least thing is</l>
               <l>In him, which you so much seem to admire.</l>
               <l>Th' Almighty power of God doth him inspire,</l>
               <l>And what not any mortall mind can reach,</l>
               <l>(14) A Heavenly Spirit doth, within, him teach.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jud.</speaker>
               <l>What gallery's this of such an ample space,</l>
               <l>Which with three sides doth the whole house embrace?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <l>The King, to's friend who beares an open hand,</l>
               <l>Upon Ionian pillars did command</l>
               <l>This to be built.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jud.</speaker>
               <l>May I within it see?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <l>You may, and it well worth your sight will be.</l>
               <l>Here curious pictures by rare pencils wrought</l>
               <l>Are added, which to strangers hither brought</l>
               <l>Might <hi>Sophompaneas</hi> acts and honors show,</l>
               <l>And where hee his own history might know.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jud.</speaker>
               <l>Let's enter therefore. Fear not <hi>Benjamin,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>We will not leave thee, we will keep within</l>
               <l>Thy sight, and all thy brethren will appear,</l>
               <l>When the great Presidents door we open hear.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <l>Run o're these pieces with a nimble eye.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>What doth this angry woman signifie,</l>
               <l>With locks all torn, whose cheeks are wet and red,</l>
               <l>VVhich hath his cloak snatcht up who from her fled?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <l>A Lady great and fair, whom lust did sting,</l>
               <l>Being denyed, on the chast youth doth fling</l>
               <l>Her crime, and palliates her sin with sin.</l>
               <l>His Garment to her lie must credit win.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:205034:27"/>
               <speaker>Jud.</speaker>
               <l>I see a dark and loathsome prison.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <l>There</l>
               <l>He of anothers fault the blame doth bear.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>What's he, who from three branches of a Vine</l>
               <l>Pressing the grapes in the Kings Cup poures wine?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <l>This is no reall story. One who was</l>
               <l>A prisoner with <hi>Sophompaneas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Had such a dream, which he interpreted;</l>
               <l>That when the Sun had thrice his radiant head</l>
               <l>In Heaven advanced, the King would as before</l>
               <l>Him to his place of Cup-bearer restore.</l>
               <l>The event proves him a Prophet. But alas,</l>
               <l>How soon are benefits forgot! His place,</l>
               <l>Wealth, favour, honour, having now again</l>
               <l>Recover'd, he unmindfull did remain</l>
               <l>Of former friendship, of what to him had</l>
               <l>Bin thus foretold, and of the Covenant made</l>
               <l>Between them, till his annuall course the Sun</l>
               <l>Through the (15) twelve signes had twice compleatly run.</l>
               <l>And none of the Magitians could expound</l>
               <l>The Kings dark dream: then was the Prophet found.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>Another sad and gloomy piece I see</l>
               <l>Full of all sorts of dainty bak'd meats, three</l>
               <l>Baskets, a flock of Birds the meat thence drawes</l>
               <l>Out with their beakes, and teares it with their claws.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <l>This also but a dream is of a poor</l>
               <l>Prisoner, who had chiefe Baker bin before</l>
               <l>To <hi>Pharaoh:</hi> and as the Prophet did</l>
               <l>Foretell, when the third morning forth was rid</l>
               <l>In her bright chariot, with his carkasse he</l>
               <l>The greedy birds fed hanging on a tree.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>Out of the River <hi>Nile</hi> seven oxen rise,</l>
               <l>Fat and well favour'd, which with heavy thighs</l>
               <l>Measuring the bank in a green meadow feed;</l>
               <l>Seven other follow, which the Lake doth breed</l>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:205034:28"/>
               <l>Lean and ill favour'd, which scarce having power</l>
               <l>To creep so far, those goodly Kine devoure.</l>
               <l>Seven goodly eares of corn bend with their own</l>
               <l>Weight to the ground, they yellow ripe are grown.</l>
               <l>As many other stalkes I see to lie</l>
               <l>Almost upon the ground, a withered, dry,</l>
               <l>Thin handfull, scorch'd with the Suns burning heat,</l>
               <l>And these the seven gallant ears up eat.</l>
               <l>What's he in skarlet lying sees this sight?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <l>The King. For unto him (16) in dreams by night</l>
               <l>Obscurely God seven fruitfull yeers foretold,</l>
               <l>And seven of famine. Yet none could unfold</l>
               <l>These knots, but who from prison for this thing.</l>
               <l>Was fetcht, and made his second by the King.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>I know him pictur'd in fine linnen, whom</l>
               <l>An Ivory chariot drawes, a diamond from</l>
               <l>His left hand sparkles, a gold chain hangs round</l>
               <l>About his neck, the people to the ground</l>
               <l>Bowing adore him, and his praises sing.</l>
               <l>But what are those there (17) in a treble ring</l>
               <l>Divided and distinguish'd? The first are</l>
               <l>Close girt in coats: the next prepar'd for war,</l>
               <l>Sweat under armour: the third sort in sight</l>
               <l>Appear from head to foot arrai'd in white.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <l>The people of this Kingdom by the Ile</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Philae</hi> bounded, and the sea and <hi>Nile</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He wisely hath divided in three parts,</l>
               <l>And distributing them to severall arts</l>
               <l>Had added new inventions. Behold where</l>
               <l>In the first rank the husbandmen appear;</l>
               <l>And they whose labours do sustain our lives,</l>
               <l>To lift the foaming flood up he contrives</l>
               <l>With the perpetuall motion of a wheel,</l>
               <l>Whose endlesse circlings footing never feel.</l>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:205034:28"/>
               <l>Behold there others (18) a strange sight) to tread</l>
               <l>Meal with their feet, clay with their hands to knead.</l>
               <l>The second sort are souldiers, whom in peace</l>
               <l>He hath train'd up to war: by some of these</l>
               <l>A trench is cast; others contend who most</l>
               <l>Swiftly can run in armes, and at a post</l>
               <l>Deal heaviest blows: some make a horse to bound,</l>
               <l>Curbing his tender mouth, and riding round</l>
               <l>Into a circle draw. But others strive</l>
               <l>A chariot arm'd with dreadfull hooks to drive.</l>
               <l>Some measure places out, wherein to pitch</l>
               <l>Their tents, them fencing with a bank &amp; ditch.</l>
               <l>With <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> huge quarter-staffe those armed go;</l>
               <l>These shoot an arrow from a twanging bow.</l>
               <l>These with a pole-axe in their hands to fight,</l>
               <l>Practice. See there whole troops, now to the right,</l>
               <l>Now to the left hand turning, now expos'd</l>
               <l>In a broad front, into a wedge now clos'd.</l>
               <l>The third sort to religion sequestred,</l>
               <l>From taxes free, by the Kings store are fed:</l>
               <l>And think not that they onely serve to put</l>
               <l>Sabaean odours on the Altars, but</l>
               <l>By <hi>Sophompaneas</hi> they are taught t' enquire</l>
               <l>What makes the wandering planets back retire.</l>
               <l>Why, when the Sun in <hi>Cancer</hi> is, the day</l>
               <l>Is longest: (19) whether the North-star doth stay the whole</l>
               <l>Ever at the same distance from the Pole:</l>
               <l>(20) Why heaven brings forth new stars: and through</l>
               <l>Work of the world the divine counsels they</l>
               <l>Search out as far as nature beares a swey.</l>
               <l>(21) See you those figures written in the dust?</l>
               <l>How great a surface a triangle must</l>
               <l>Contain, they dispute: what proportion there</l>
               <l>The Circle hath to the Diameter.</l>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:205034:29"/>
               <l>Then all in war done valiantly, or in</l>
               <l>Peace pleasingly, what wholesome laws have bin</l>
               <l>For <hi>Aegypt</hi> made: the names of all who e're</l>
               <l>From <hi>Mziraim</hi> their first King the Crown did wear</l>
               <l>At <hi>Memphis,</hi> all the peoples dreadfull stormes,</l>
               <l>Mysteriously in (22) Hieroglyphicke formes</l>
               <l>About the vast high (23) Pyramids they cut,</l>
               <l>And signes of things not sounds of words there put.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>What's by that picture meant, where to the Court</l>
               <l>Such multitudes trembling and pale resort?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <l>(24) A businesse of great moment, for the King</l>
               <l>Is agitated. When no crop did spring</l>
               <l>Up the first yeer, hunger did them compell▪</l>
               <l>(Their money being spent) their slaves to sell</l>
               <l>For corn, which by the Prophet warn'd, in store</l>
               <l>The King had hoarded. When the famine more</l>
               <l>Cruelly pinch'd, they then bring all their breed</l>
               <l>Of Oxen, and what other Cattell feed</l>
               <l>In the green pastures: then they morgage all</l>
               <l>Their Lands, and afterward themselves inthrall.</l>
               <l>So all those grounds which the great <hi>Nile</hi> doth see,</l>
               <l>Except what to the Priests allotted bee;</l>
               <l>And all the people by the King were bought,</l>
               <l>Whom to forsake (for this the Governour thought</l>
               <l>To be the Kingdomes safety) he commands,</l>
               <l>Where long their ancestors had dwelt, the Lands,</l>
               <l>And in strange places he new Colonies</l>
               <l>Hath planted.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>O how politique and wise</l>
               <l>His Counsels are! whether long use or Heaven</l>
               <l>Such wisdome from above to him hath given!</l>
               <l>But lest this may us hurt, my heart to fear</l>
               <l>Hath cause; I wish that he lesse knowing were.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <l>On that side of the Gallery behind</l>
               <l>The house, there nothing is, which you may find</l>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:205034:29"/>
               <l>Worth looking on. There he foreknowing all</l>
               <l>The fates hereafter <hi>Aegypt</hi> to befall,</l>
               <l>Hath them dispos'd. These now are in a flood</l>
               <l>Of darknesse drown'd, but shall be understood,</l>
               <l>When time shall make the truth break forth like day.</l>
               <l>And now the fearfull Lad for us doth stay.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
               <l>(25) <hi>NIle,</hi> or if <hi>Siris</hi> rather we,</l>
               <l>Or, (26) with our parents better thee</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Astapus</hi> call, who from a spring</l>
               <l>Unknown through desarts wandring</l>
               <l>Deep under ground, where thou for men</l>
               <l>May'st usefull rise, break'st out agen,</l>
               <l>And from high rocks down falling mak'st</l>
               <l>An horrid murmur, and thence tak'st</l>
               <l>A double course, which gently glides</l>
               <l>Embracing <hi>Aegypt</hi> on both sides;</l>
               <l>Until far spreading with seven wide</l>
               <l>Channels it doth the sea divide.</l>
               <l>(27) What shall I say a Virgin, when</l>
               <l>We hear so many learned men</l>
               <l>To differ, whom my Lord doth call</l>
               <l>Often to dine with him? what shall</l>
               <l>I say, the direfull causes be,</l>
               <l>That thou wont <hi>Aegypt</hi> formerly</l>
               <l>To water so, (28) it had no need</l>
               <l>Of rain from Heaven, wilt not exceed</l>
               <l>Eight cubits, nor the (29) dog-star though (30)</l>
               <l>Thus often call, wilt higher flow?</l>
               <l>Is the Sun by conjunction</l>
               <l>Of other stars now hotter grown.</l>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:205034:30"/>
               <l>And <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> where I first</l>
               <l>Did nourishment receive, such thirst,</l>
               <l>And drought now feel she can no more,</l>
               <l>(31) Her Rain into thy river poure?</l>
               <l>Or whether doth (32) slow <hi>Saturn</hi> ty</l>
               <l>Up the swift Planet (33) <hi>Mercury,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To vegetate thy course ordain'd?</l>
               <l>(34) Or hath the frozen west restrain'd</l>
               <l>His vernall blasts which make thee swell,</l>
               <l>And o're the banks thy flood compell?</l>
               <l>Or doth the falling earth deny</l>
               <l>Unto thy streams their old supply,</l>
               <l>Whil'st, (35) which the world begirts, the great</l>
               <l>Ocean whose waves on Atlas beat,</l>
               <l>By a blind passage, and through hidden</l>
               <l>Caverns to go it hath forbidden?</l>
               <l>(36) Or hath it stopt the secret way</l>
               <l>By which thy fellow flouds convey</l>
               <l>Themselves and joyn by stealth with thee?</l>
               <l>These things I doubt o're-wisely yee</l>
               <l>In vain seek. (37) God the world who made,</l>
               <l>And when the water did invade</l>
               <l>Ill mingled earth, the liquid deep</l>
               <l>Did teach in shoars and banks to keep;</l>
               <l>Hath made <hi>Nile</hi> also, whom he in</l>
               <l>A Law hath bound, which hating sin</l>
               <l>He changeth, and this age doth fright,</l>
               <l>This wicked age, that so he might</l>
               <l>By prodigies mankind (in all</l>
               <l>Vice lost) to virtue thus recall.</l>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="act">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:205034:30"/>
            <head>The Fourth Act.</head>
            <stage>Joseph, Iudah, Benjamin.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>VNbind the Lad there, that more freely hee</l>
               <l>May answer, and yee of my guard, and yee</l>
               <l>(38) O Nubians, and my faithfull train be gone;</l>
               <l>A while I with these guests will talk alone.</l>
               <l>(39) Lives the old man your Sire, of whom yee spake?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>He liv'd, when hither we did our journey take.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>How great an age was he arriv'd at then?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>He had seen almost sixscore yeers and ten.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>Is such declining age from sicknesse free?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>Sorrow except, else no disease hath he.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>Doth he mourn for the absence of this Lad?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>He hath another griefe that makes him sad.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>May not I know? I have a Sire that's old.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>He grieves for a lost son, I late you told.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>What cruell chance bereav'd him of his son?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>God knows, before whose eyes all things are done.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>To vouch him who knows all things you do well.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>The certainty no mortall can us tell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>By time things hidden oft discover'd be.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>O if that wish'd for day I once might see!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>That to his Father him restore you may.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>Could my death purchase't, Ile make no delay.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>So dear unto his Father was the Lad?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>No son a more fond father ever had.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jos.</speaker>
               <l>Was't for his honest and not envious mind?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>And a rare towardnesse that in him shin'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:205034:31"/>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>Say, what your thoughts of this great kingdom are.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>It may with the best Syrian Lands compare.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>Do ye the Government, and Laws approve?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>All things, you governing, our wonder move.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>And would you in this Country now remain?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>Gladly: lest famine us invade again.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>Hence to depart what therefore doth you make?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>Our Sire at home left we must not forsake.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>May not the old man hither too be brought?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>He must resolve that; obey him I ought.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>Love of his son perhaps may draw him here.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>This child was also ever to him dear.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>What name he call'd him by, to know I crave.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Benjamin</hi> is the name his Father gave.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>Therein's an omen of a strong right hand.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>How's that? Do you the Hebrew understand?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>I formerly did in your Country dwell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>What brought you hither, I beseech you tell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>Envy, though unprovok'd, a cruell beast.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>That monster in our Land is no strange guest.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>Are free born bodies there wont to be sold?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>This is by (40) custome and sharp lawes control'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>Many things done against the lawes I see.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>Which, if men fail, by God will punisht be.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>Now say what was his name whom yee did lose.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioseph.</hi> That name his parents did impose.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>What in your language noted is thereby?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>It to our house <hi>Increase</hi> doth signifie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>The thing doth often with the name agree.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>But the event proves this name vain to be.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>Nothing's too hard for God. Never despair.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>O that God would grant this, though hopeles, pray'r.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>He hath, and will. Look here on me. I am</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioseph,</hi> my Brethren. Me another name</l>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:205034:31"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aegypt</hi> hath given. Behold, your eyes now see,</l>
               <l>How God hath my estate <hi>Increas'd.</hi> Hence be</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dothan,</hi> the threats of death, and dreadfull pit,</l>
               <l>And the Arabian Merchants banisht quite</l>
               <l>Out of your mindes. Let my dreams credit have:</l>
               <l>This is enough. No more of you I crave.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
               <l>Excellent Prince; For Brother I not dare</l>
               <l>To call you, since our guilty looks declare</l>
               <l>We have not dealt with you like Brethren, now</l>
               <l>Again we suppliants, miserable bow</l>
               <l>Down at your knees, not that we may not sterve,</l>
               <l>But that you from your selfe would us preserve.</l>
               <l>Pardon us. VVearied with long griefe our Sire</l>
               <l>Doth this intreat, or, if you will, require.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>Cast away care. You aske too late wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is</l>
               <l>Already granted. To forgive you, 'tis</l>
               <l>Too light. As Brethren I a Brother you</l>
               <l>Do love, whereas to <hi>Benjamin</hi> a true</l>
               <l>Affection I see you bear, which I</l>
               <l>Have long by circumstances sought to try.</l>
               <l>That this not grieve you the felicity</l>
               <l>Of the event deserves. Ther's reason why</l>
               <l>I should give thankes to you, by whom I here</l>
               <l>The second honours of this Kingdom bear.</l>
               <l>God who hath all things made, o're all things whose</l>
               <l>Eyes watch, who cares for all, and doth dispose</l>
               <l>His counsels afar off, that I should bee</l>
               <l>A Saviour to you and my Father, me</l>
               <l>Hath hither sent before. Two yeers are fled,</l>
               <l>Since <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and which wont thence to be fed,</l>
               <l>The adjacent Countries hunger hath pinch'd sore;</l>
               <l>There yet remain five yeers of famine more.</l>
               <l>Go therefore to my Father who my fate</l>
               <l>Bewailes, the strange and joyfull news relate.</l>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:205034:32"/>
               <l>Whom he hath long thought dead, alive that I</l>
               <l>Not only am, but great, renown'd and high</l>
               <l>Do sit, enjoying heaps of wealth. Come yee,</l>
               <l>And of my power all partakers be.</l>
               <l>(41) Let me him happily requite, to whom</l>
               <l>I owe my birth; and let my Father come,</l>
               <l>And see, whom he hath so desir'd, his son.</l>
               <l>I'l find rich pastures for the flocks, and on</l>
               <l>The Pharian grass shall <hi>Isaacs</hi> cattell grow.</l>
               <l>My Brethren not these twenty yeers seen, O</l>
               <l>How glad am I to fall upon y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur necks!</l>
               <l>And on thine <hi>Benjamin,</hi> whose hair's like wax;</l>
               <l>Which here I take delight to touch, and stand</l>
               <l>Leaning upon thy shoulders with each hand.</l>
               <l>The tears run down my cheekes, how I rejoyce,</l>
               <l>My weeping speaks, though it hath drown'd my voice.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <l>Hail, who with me of <hi>Rachel</hi> the same mother</l>
               <l>Wert born; here found, but yet unlook'd for Brother.</l>
               <l>A man, a child, a Prince, me wrong'd protect:</l>
               <l>With what art you rule <hi>Aegypt,</hi> me direct:</l>
               <l>And that these teares, signes of true love, I may</l>
               <l>Now pour upon thy neck, permit I pray.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>O day I never hop'd to see,</l>
               <l>How great my joyes are made by thee!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <l>Now I my journey not repent,</l>
               <l>That down I into <hi>Aegypt</hi> went:</l>
               <l>Nor falsely accus'd that I bands</l>
               <l>Did wear upon my innocent hands.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>Sorry I am that you did bear</l>
               <l>Such imputation, and such fear</l>
               <l>Were in: this was my wile to prove,</l>
               <l>Whether your Brethren did you love.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <l>I much have gain'd them thus to clear,</l>
               <l>Nor can I think the price too dear.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:205034:32"/>
               <speaker>Jos.</speaker>
               <l>Now is my life more sweet, since I</l>
               <l>Have found my Brethrens piety.</l>
               <l>More glad I was not in that day,</l>
               <l>When I from prison came away;</l>
               <l>And when the King himself and (42) all</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Memphis</hi> did me their Father call.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <l>Brother to see your happiness,</l>
               <l>I feel more joyes then I expresse.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jos.</speaker>
               <l>What thou seest mine,</l>
               <l>Brother, is thine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <l>O how will our old Father be</l>
               <l>O'rejoy'd together us to see!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jos.</speaker>
               <l>Hee'l come, hee'l come: ye shall not stay,</l>
               <l>With such a train I'l you away</l>
               <l>Send, as becomes the Governors,</l>
               <l>Both Brethren and Ambassadors.</l>
               <l>But we hereafter shall have time enough</l>
               <l>These pleasures to enjoy. My hour's come now,</l>
               <l>Wherein such conference I with the King</l>
               <l>Am wont to have, as the day forth doth bring;</l>
               <l>Or such as may be fit for him to hear.</l>
               <l>Ye fellows of my guard again appear.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Judah, Reuben, Benjamin.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jud.</speaker>
               <l>Though on the constant faith and piety</l>
               <l>Of a kind brother I am bid rely;</l>
               <l>The very face yet of wrong'd innocence,</l>
               <l>And his remembrance of our dire offence,</l>
               <l>Such terror and amazement in me wrought,</l>
               <l>As after a few words which I scarce brought</l>
               <l>Out, all this while I nothing more could say.</l>
               <l>Now thee, whom he doth chiefly love, we pray;</l>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:205034:33"/>
               <l>A branch of the same womb, not guilty, free</l>
               <l>From blame: make him propitious to us, be</l>
               <l>The pious peace-maker. He looking on</l>
               <l>Thee, favouring thee may drink oblivion.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reu.</speaker>
               <l>What <hi>Iudah</hi> hath said the same words believe</l>
               <l>We all say. If thou ever didst receive</l>
               <l>From us thy Brethren any kindnesse, now</l>
               <l>Requite it. The thing easie is which thou</l>
               <l>May'st do; yet unto us it of no small</l>
               <l>Importance is. Do what we ever shall</l>
               <l>Take delight to remember. So may thee</l>
               <l>At home in safety thy old Father see.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <l>As I conceive, this needs not. Yet will I</l>
               <l>Not have it said, that I my help deny</l>
               <l>To my dear Brethren; when I came away,</l>
               <l>My Father me instructing thus did say.</l>
               <l>O son, hate none, but yet (43) to them be kind</l>
               <l>Chiefly, whom blood doth neerest to thee bind.</l>
               <l>Them to retain, by suffering seek, and not</l>
               <l>Only by duties. <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Lot</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVas such an Unkle. As who did expose</l>
               <l>His own life, that he might from savage foes</l>
               <l>Him rescue by his sword, and back he brings</l>
               <l>Victoriously (44) the spoiles home of four Kings.</l>
               <l>And to avoid the strife of bounds, the East</l>
               <l>He quite forsaking far did travell West.</l>
               <l>So mocking <hi>Ismael,</hi> though his mother were</l>
               <l>A bond slave, <hi>Isaac</hi> patiently did bear.</l>
               <l>And that I of my selfe may something adde,</l>
               <l>When my fierce natur'd brother <hi>Esau</hi> had</l>
               <l>Threatned to kill me, twenty yeeres I led</l>
               <l>A wandering life, and from his presence fled</l>
               <l>An exile, that the length of time might tame,</l>
               <l>And tire his anger, and when home I came,</l>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:205034:33"/>
               <l>Him swelling big, I although innocent,</l>
               <l>With gifts and humble prayer made to relent.</l>
               <l>These Lessons my good Father gave, which I</l>
               <l>Not onely have to faithfull memory</l>
               <l>Committed, but will them perform in deeds.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jud.</speaker>
               <l>Brave issue, which from <hi>Rachels</hi> wombe proceeds!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
               <l>FAme flying to my eares</l>
               <l>Good tidings swiftly beares,</l>
               <l>The Governour hath found</l>
               <l>His Brethren: a glad sound</l>
               <l>To Priest-born <hi>Asenath</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Daughter of <hi>Potiphrath;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Since she hath understood</l>
               <l>Her Lord of noble blood:</l>
               <l>Whose Ancestors of great</l>
               <l>Antiquity a seat</l>
               <l>Had in those parts, in which</l>
               <l>(45) Euphrates making rich,</l>
               <l>And then a shaft more fleet</l>
               <l>(46) Tigris, twice mingling meet.</l>
               <l>From this ground God did take</l>
               <l>The dust, which he did make</l>
               <l>A man (47) in his own image,</l>
               <l>From whom mankind his linage</l>
               <l>Derives, in whom all wee</l>
               <l>Conclude our pedigree.</l>
               <l>Then six daies work he shut</l>
               <l>Up, and an end here put,</l>
               <l>God having man created,</l>
               <l>Nought greater meditated.</l>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:205034:34"/>
               <l>For him of his free grace</l>
               <l>He gave a mind and face,</l>
               <l>Which Heaven might contemplate;</l>
               <l>Then long to propagate</l>
               <l>His seed, he from his side</l>
               <l>A rib took, a fair Bride</l>
               <l>Which to the man became,</l>
               <l>Whose heart felt a new flame,</l>
               <l>Assoon as he did wake,</l>
               <l>(48) And sleep his limbes forsake.</l>
               <l>Hence is the marriage knot,</l>
               <l>A holier there is not:</l>
               <l>Whence, a beloved name</l>
               <l>To Parents, Children came.</l>
               <l>The babe on's mothers nipple,</l>
               <l>A veine of milke doth tipple.</l>
               <l>Brethren come next behind,</l>
               <l>Whom seeds of birth fast bind.</l>
               <l>As horses running neigh,</l>
               <l>And with their fellows play:</l>
               <l>Or under one yoaks law</l>
               <l>Oxen together draw.</l>
               <l>O that (49) the Phenix on</l>
               <l>Her wings of Cinnamon</l>
               <l>Which smell (50) of whose rare kind,</l>
               <l>But one the VVorld can find,</l>
               <l>Would through the air me bear</l>
               <l>To Aethiopia, where</l>
               <l>(Who too much Sun-burnt bee)</l>
               <l>My Brethren I might see.</l>
               <l>But yonder, before whom the Priest doth bring</l>
               <l>(51) The sacred fire, comes the Aegyptian King.</l>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="act">
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:205034:34"/>
            <head>The Fifth Act.</head>
            <stage>Pharaoh, Joseph, Judah, Chorus.</stage>
            <l>THee having gratulated, thy wife I</l>
            <l>The honour now of her affinity</l>
            <l>VVill gratulate too. Thy deservings can</l>
            <l>Be equal'd by no favours: thou the man</l>
            <l>Art by whose aid no cares my breast annoy,</l>
            <l>By whom my Kingdom freely I enjoy.</l>
            <l>To thee her safety <hi>Aegypt</hi> owes, and I</l>
            <l>My quiet. That all wast the fields not lie</l>
            <l>By men forsaken, that the plow doth lift</l>
            <l>The earth up to new hopes, is all thy gift.</l>
            <l>And therefore to thy honours I will this</l>
            <l>Have to be added, as the manner is</l>
            <l>Of th' Eastern Nation, that a place in heaven</l>
            <l>Unto thy name among the stars be given.</l>
            <l>And the field-tiller the (1) coelestiall Bull</l>
            <l>Of thy full merit shall be made a full</l>
            <l>And lasting monument, as a place great <hi>Cham</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Old <hi>Mizraims</hi> Sire hath in (2) the neighbouring ram.</l>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jos.</speaker>
               <l>So many honours and so great on me</l>
               <l>(3) Your Majesty hath heap'd, as I would be</l>
               <l>Rather eas'd of the burthen, then it have</l>
               <l>Made heavier. Yet why I something crave,</l>
               <l>My Brethren are the cause, and hither whom</l>
               <l>With them I would have out of <hi>Syria</hi> come</l>
               <l>My Father. They by occupation are</l>
               <l>Shepherds. A pleasant Land there lies not far</l>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:205034:35"/>
               <l>From (4) <hi>Heliopolis,</hi> where grasse still green,</l>
               <l>And pastures ever flourishing are seen.</l>
               <l>The bordering Pelusians it call</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Goshen.</hi> This Land hath hitherto been all</l>
               <l>Lost to the use of men, (5) because your Nation</l>
               <l>Holds every Shepherd an abomination.</l>
               <l>These grounds if on my kindred you bestow,</l>
               <l>I promise it shall to the profit grow</l>
               <l>Of them and <hi>Aegypt.</hi> See, in words what I,</l>
               <l>They by their gestures beg, and prostrate lie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jud.</speaker>
               <l>Long may the Mighty Pharian Monarch live.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phar.</speaker>
               <l>Rise up: I for your flocks will pastures give;</l>
               <l>And, your whole house and Father to convey,</l>
               <l>VVaggons, and fit provision for the way:</l>
               <l>And the best things which fruitfull <hi>Aegypt</hi> can</l>
               <l>Afford, a present for the good old man.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ios.</speaker>
               <l>Give me leave that I may this adde. You see</l>
               <l>Under your government a people free</l>
               <l>Come voluntarily. O then let none</l>
               <l>To change their Rites and their Religion</l>
               <l>Ever compell them. If they have a minde</l>
               <l>Hence to depart, either because they finde,</l>
               <l>That some calamity will them befall,</l>
               <l>Or because better hopes away them call,</l>
               <l>Let none forbid them. May pure air so blesse</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and <hi>Nilus</hi> keep a just increase;</l>
               <l>And mothers with a numerous issue fill</l>
               <l>The Land, and your race sway the scepter still.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phar.</speaker>
               <l>By him, who all things can o're-rule, I sweare,</l>
               <l>(6) And this my head and successors I here</l>
               <l>For ever bind; that their Religion free</l>
               <l>To th' Hebrews, their departure safe shall bee.</l>
               <l>If any King hereafter break this oath,</l>
               <l>May foaming <hi>Nilus</hi> with a bloody froath</l>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:205034:35"/>
               <l>Colour the Ocean, loathsome Frogs the ground</l>
               <l>Cover, and in the bed-chambers abound.</l>
               <l>A raging Murrain on the cattell light;</l>
               <l>No herbs look green, the corn a tempest smite.</l>
               <l>Nor fruit nor leaves on any tree remain,</l>
               <l>With torrid ulcers vext may men complaine.</l>
               <l>Thick darknesse, such as in th'infernall shade</l>
               <l>Is to be felt, the face of heaven invade.</l>
               <l>Night follow night without a glimpse of day,</l>
               <l>Through every house the pestilence display,</l>
               <l>A sad infection, and the first-born kill,</l>
               <l>Which may with woefull cries the City fill.</l>
               <l>If this be not enough, in the profound</l>
               <l>Red sea may the whole Nation be drown'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jos.</speaker>
               <l>Nor shall it be rich Pharian soil, in vain,</l>
               <l>That thou the Hebrews e're didst entertain.</l>
               <l>Whil'st to a race belov'd of God, thou kind</l>
               <l>Shalt prove, all things to prosper thou shalt find</l>
               <l>Above thy wish. Nature her self shall bee</l>
               <l>Thy handmaid. There will come an age with thee</l>
               <l>When of our Nation famous Kings shall make</l>
               <l>A League, and (7) Israel a wife shall take</l>
               <l>From <hi>Aegypt.</hi> Again some of th' Hebrew Nation</l>
               <l>Shall hither come and make (8) a new plantation.</l>
               <l>Afterwards, when descending from the skies</l>
               <l>He foretold by so many Prophesies,</l>
               <l>The Worlds Redeemer, Prince of piety,</l>
               <l>Shall visit mortals, he shall hither fly.</l>
               <l>A faithfull place of refuge this shall be,</l>
               <l>And (9) safe to him an infant exile. Hee</l>
               <l>The same Lawes both unto my Country-men</l>
               <l>The Hebrews, and unto th' Egyptians then</l>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:205034:36"/>
               <l>Shall give, and <hi>Nile</hi> and <hi>Iordan</hi> teach in one</l>
               <l>Channell to meet of (10) pure Religion.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
               <l>(11) PArtakers of so great a good may wee</l>
               <l>In <hi>Aethiopia</hi> also be;</l>
               <l>And our hearts burn with a coelestiall heat,</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Phaebus</hi> more divine and great.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:205034:36"/>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:205034:37"/>
            <p>FOr the satisfaction of the Printer, and not so much to illustrate any passage in this (though short, not obscure) Poem, as increase the bulk, rather, then the price, these <hi>Annotations</hi> are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented: Which for the most part (wherein I please my selfe, and shall, I hope, others) I have gleaned out of the rich crops of <hi>Vossius</hi> and <hi>Grotius</hi> themselves.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="commentary">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:205034:37"/>
            <head>ANNOTATIONS ON THE FIRST ACT.</head>
            <p n="1">(1) <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ut of his chamber]</hi> or veile, as our English Geneva translation hath it in the marginall note, <hi>Psal.</hi> 19. <hi>v.</hi> 6. Upon which <hi>Aretius Felinus</hi> a Commentator: The manner was among the Hebrews, and is obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved even at this day, that having spred a vaile they deliver the Bride to the Bridegroom under it, out of which he comming forth exhilarates all, and the wedding feast begins. To which also <hi>Jo. Baptist</hi> allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded when he said, <hi>The friend of the Bridegroom re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceth, when he heareth the Bridegrooms voice,</hi> Jo. 3.29. So, the sun rising, and the morning putting forth its golden head into the world, the face of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse is in a wonderfull manner refreshed, and as it were renewed.</p>
            <p>I may here commend the Author for taking a simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude (sutable to the argument, and person of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seph</hi>) out of the Holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Hee observes also the Law of the best Dramaticks,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:205034:38"/> who (usually) begin the Action with the Morning, and keep within the compasse of one day.</p>
            <p n="2">(2) <hi>Where God wee may behold]</hi> For the invisible things of him from the creation of the world, are cleerly seen, being understood by the things that are made, even his eternall power, and Godhead.— <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20.</p>
            <p n="3">(3) <hi>Mentall light]</hi> What the Sun is to our sense, that is God to our understanding: and as we see not the Sun, but by the light of the Sun; so neither do we see God, but by the spirituall light of himselfe. Having therefore our senses enlightned, we must turn our mind towards God, that our understanding may also be enlightned, <hi>Vos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. Idol. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p n="4">(4) <hi>Whose head Heaven knowes]</hi> As for the originall Of <hi>Nilus,</hi> which many both Ancient and Modern VVriters have delivered to be utterly unknown, <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lostratus</hi> hath it rightly, <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>Icon. The Aepyptians indeed have the channels of Nilus, but the Aethiopi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans the fountaines.</hi> For it runnes downe from the craggy rocks, which are called the Mountaines of the Moon through <hi>Aethiopia</hi> into <hi>Aegypt,</hi> which is rightly hinted by <hi>Paulus Jovius l.</hi> 18. <hi>Hist. sui temp. &amp; Hierom. Osorius l</hi> 9. <hi>de gestis Emanuelis.</hi> But before it rusheth from the mountaines, it makes a huge Lake: of which also <hi>Pansanias</hi> makes mention, <hi>l.</hi> 5. And experience hath confirmed the truth of it; as we may see out of <hi>Nicolaus Leonicus, l.</hi> 2. <hi>de Var. Hist. c.</hi> 56. The Country where it riseth is called <hi>Goyome;</hi> and is in the jurisdiction of the King of the Abyssines, who also in his Imperiall titles (among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther)
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:205034:38"/> writes, <hi>King of Goyome, where Nilus riseth.</hi> Witnesse the King of <hi>Aethiopia David</hi> in his letters to <hi>Emanuel</hi> King of <hi>Portugal:</hi> and out of them <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mianus à Goes,</hi> a Portugal. <hi>Voss. de Idolol. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 75.</p>
            <p n="5">(5) <hi>Beames from Libanus]</hi> Or (in the Scriptures) <hi>Lebanon.</hi> A mountainous forrest, whence <hi>Solomon</hi> was furnished with Cedars by <hi>Hiram</hi> King of <hi>Tyre,</hi> for the building of the Temple.</p>
            <p n="6">(6) <hi>Groves within my house]</hi> Groves, saith <hi>Festus,</hi> signifie pleasant woods, such as the Ancients had within the inclosures of their houses
<q>
                  <bibl>Hor. l. <hi>3.</hi> od. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <l>—With what a noise the wood</l>
                  <l>Among fair buildings scituate</l>
                  <l>Rebellowes to the wind.</l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>And</hi> Epist. ad Fusc.</bibl>
                  <l>A grove among pillars of marble growes.</l>
                  <l>And woods in houses like our sacred groves,</l>
                  <l>And gilded doors, and marble floors. <bibl>
                        <hi>Tibul. l. 3.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </l>
                  <bibl>Torrentius <hi>upon</hi> Sueton. Aug. c. <hi>72.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Where likewise <hi>Casaubon:</hi> the more elegant sort of Romans were so taken with <hi>groves,</hi> that even in their City houses, if they could in no other place, they would at the least have them on their house tops, <hi>Jo. Schildius Commentar. in Sueton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Live they not contrary to nature, who plant Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards on their highest turrets? Whose woods shake over the roofes and tops of their houses, their rootes springing up thence, where their tops should hardly have reached. <hi>Senec. Epist.</hi> 122. Upon which <hi>Lipsius:</hi> Gardens and Groves on the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:205034:39"/> and tops of their houses. As wee have seen in the Royall City of <hi>Brussels:</hi> but upon flat tops, and without a ridge; where the earth was mounted on beames, or arches of brick. <hi>Seneca de Ira.</hi> 1. <hi>c. ult.</hi> calls it, <hi>to suspend woods.</hi> Which the other <hi>Seneca</hi> gives a touch of, in <hi>Thyestes:</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>—On my house top no wood</l>
                  <l>There planted waves.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And</hi> Woods climbe up the house tops,</l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Plin. l. 15. c. 14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nero</hi> built a house, in which precious stones and gold were not so much wondered at (as a thing long us'd, and by superfluous ryot common) as the fields and pooles, in manner of a wildernesse; on the one side woods, on the other spacious fields and prospects. <hi>Tacit. Annal. l.</hi> 15. <hi>c.</hi> 10. See <hi>Nero's</hi> golden house in <hi>Suetonius</hi> and <hi>Hackwels Apol. l.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>I conclude with our Author:
<q>
                  <l>Groves over the roofe tops, and lakes within,</l>
                  <l>A house containes what every where hath bin.</l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>H. Grot. Farrag. l. 2.</hi> In <hi>Jo. Meursii. de luxu Rom. librum.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="7">(7) <hi>Strange beasts from Africk.]</hi> Our Author, I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, by <hi>a medio die,</hi> meanes the Meridian or South parts of <hi>Africk;</hi> and alludes to an old proverbe: <hi>Afrca still brings forth some new creature.</hi> Nor is <hi>Aegypt</hi> it self (say some Geographers) in <hi>Africk,</hi> but in the borders of <hi>Asia,</hi> and next unto <hi>Africk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">(8) <hi>Wool from boughs by the Seres comb'd.]</hi> The
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:205034:39"/>
               <hi>Seres</hi> are a people of the East. From this Nation silke (cal'd in Latine <hi>Sericum</hi>) was brought into <hi>Persia:</hi> From <hi>Persia,</hi> conquer'd by <hi>Alexander,</hi> into <hi>Greece.</hi> From <hi>Greece,</hi> the Roman Empire flourishing, into <hi>Rome;</hi> where a pound of silk was sold for a pound of gold. Untill <hi>Justinian</hi> the Emperour not liking to pay so dear for garments to the Persian his enemy, by good hap two Monks came out of <hi>India,</hi> who told <hi>Caesar</hi> of the silk-wormes, and that the wormes could not be brought to <hi>Constantinople,</hi> but the eggs might, out of which the worms would breed. The Monks therefore were sent back to fetch the eggs. And from hence is all that kind of silk-wormes, which we have at this day in <hi>Europe.</hi> But the more vulgar opinion was, that silke was carded or comb'd from the boughs and barkes of trees. Whence <hi>Virgil.</hi> 2. <hi>Geor. v.</hi> 120.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Or th' Aethiopian woods white with soft wool?</l>
               <l>Fine flecces how from leaves the Seres pull?</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Vos. Idol. l. 4. c. 90.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p n="9">(9) <hi>At Babylon with skilful needles wrought.]</hi> The Veil of the Temple at <hi>Hierusalem</hi> is described by <hi>Josephus,</hi> to consist of violet, purple and scarlet-silk cunningly mixt and wrought by Babylonian Needles. <hi>Sands An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notat.</hi> on <hi>Christus Pat. Act</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 296.</p>
            <p n="10">(10) <hi>Pearles a present from the Indian.]</hi> Among the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians and Persians Pearles are found in hard white shels of sea fish, and bred at a certaine time of the yeere by mixture of dew, which they take in with often gaping. That this kind of jewell also, though not so good, is bred and gathered in the Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:205034:40"/> sea wee are not ignorant. <hi>Ammian. Marcellin.</hi> And to the like purpose <hi>Pliny, l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 35. It is certain that small and discoloured Pearls are bred in <hi>Britta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> whereas the commendation of them consists in whitenesse, greatnesse, roundnesse, smoothnesse, weight: yet in hope of the Brittish pearles, such as they were, <hi>Julius Caesar,</hi> saith <hi>Suetonius,</hi> first went into <hi>Brittaine,</hi> and consecrated a Brest-plate of them to <hi>Venus</hi> his progenitrix. See Sir <hi>H. Savil,</hi> upon <hi>Tacit.</hi> in the life of <hi>Agricola.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will speak first of pearls, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> saith, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in the very name. The Latines call them <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones,</hi> not because there are never two found together, but because no two are found unsever'd. That the shels open and shut themselves is certain enough. But they are said to open in the night, that from the Lunar aspersion, that is, the dew, they may conceive. This is <hi>Pliny</hi>'s opinion, and thence of <hi>Solinus,</hi> and from him of <hi>Ammian, Marcel.</hi> But though this may bee true of the Land shell, yet it will bee false of the sea shell, as even this is an argument, that whereas of the shels some are at the bottome, others float, and swim on the top of the sea; these on the superficies are the least. I know they may answer, the shels goe to the bottome assoon as they have conceived: but the shells having the biggest Pearles are bred in the bottome, and wander not, but stick there, so that the Diver must often sink twenty fathome for them. <hi>Vossi. Idol. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 47.</p>
            <p n="11">(11) Ambition did not a great Table spread.]</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Luc. l. 4.</hi>
                  </bibl>O luxury too prodigall of things!</l>
               <l>Content with no provision easily brought;</l>
               <l>Ambitious hunger for things dearly sought</l>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:205034:40"/>
               <l>O're land and sea, pride of a sumptuous table,</l>
               <l>See what small store to cherish life is able,</l>
               <l>And nature please: these souldiers fainting souls,</l>
               <l>No unknown Consul's noble wine in bowls</l>
               <l>Of myrrh and gold restores; from fountains pure</l>
               <l>Water and bread their fleeting lives assure.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>T. MAY.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p n="12">(12) <hi>Mandrake.] Grotius,</hi> I beleeve, alludes to <hi>Josephs</hi> elder brother <hi>Reubens</hi> Mandrakes, and a place in the <hi>Canticles</hi> 7.14. where they are spoken of as a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant fruit; Though they which are cal'd so among us are not so. And <hi>Iunius</hi> and <hi>Tremellius</hi> translate the word, <hi>amabiles flores.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No sparkling wines of Meroe.]</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Luc. 1.10.</hi>
                  </bibl>In golden plate they fill their feasting boards,</l>
               <l>With what the air the earth or Nile affords,</l>
               <l>What luxury with vain ambition had</l>
               <l>Sought through the world, and not as hunger bade,</l>
               <l>Beasts, fowls, the Gods of Egypt are devour'd,</l>
               <l>From Chrystall Ewres is Niles water powr'd</l>
               <l>Upon their hands: studded with gems that shine,</l>
               <l>Their bowles containe no Mareotick wine,</l>
               <l>But strong and sparkling wines of Meroe.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>T. M.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p n="13">(13) <hi>Zythum]</hi> Is a drink made of Barley. <hi>Theophrastus</hi> saith, that there is a wine made of Barley and Wheat, which the Aegyptians call <hi>Zythum.</hi> See <hi>Hierome</hi> upon <hi>Esay, c.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p n="14">(14) <hi>A Well]</hi> See the wells digg'd by <hi>Isaac, Gen.</hi> 24. And <hi>Jacobs</hi> well. <hi>Jo.</hi> 4.6.</p>
            <p n="15">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:205034:41"/>(15) <hi>Timbrell]</hi> Or <hi>Sistrum.</hi> A musicall Instrument pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar (it seemes) to the Egyptians. And therefore <hi>Virgil</hi> of <hi>Cleopatra:</hi>
               <q>
                  <p>The Queen her troops with her own <hi>Sistrum</hi> cals.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Aenead. l 8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And</hi> Lucan,
<q>She with her <hi>Sistrum</hi> frights the Capitoll. <bibl>
                     <hi>l. 10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="16">(16) <hi>Hunger no allegiance knowes.]</hi>
               <bibl>Luc. l. 3.</bibl>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Corn most stirs their hate most draws their loves,</l>
               <l>And only Famine to rebellion moves</l>
               <l>Cities; and fear is bought, where great men feed</l>
               <l>The slothful Commons: nought starv'd people dread.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>T. M.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p n="17">(17) <hi>I'le charge the Lad that he my cup did steal.]</hi> An example perhaps of a blamelesse untruth (<hi>Philo</hi> also commending it) may be given in <hi>Joseph,</hi> who being the Kings Vicegerent and in highest authority, feig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly, and not so thinking, accuseth his Brethren, first as spies, then as thieves, <hi>Grot. d. jure bell. ac pac. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1 § 15.</p>
            <p>And so parents, Schoolmasters, Tutors and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates may understand our English proverbe. <hi>Tell a lie, and find a truth.</hi> We allow likewise Physitians and nurses to say to a child or patient, that a bitter potion is sweet, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="18">(18) <hi>Power is but frail.]</hi> Therefore if wee are plac'd amid'st the noise of Cities, let a Monitor stand by our side, and against praysers of great patrimonies com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend him that is rich with a little, and measures
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:205034:41"/> wealth by the use. Against them who extoll favour and power, let him set leasure imploy'd in studies and a mind turn'd back from externall things to its owne. Let him shew these in the vulgar opinion happy ones, trembling and astonish'd at their owne envyed height, and thinking far otherwise of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves then they are esteem'd by others: For what unto others seem high places, unto themselves are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipices. Then are they heartlesse and quaking as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as they look down from that steep height of their greatnesse; For they think on the various casualties, and most slippery to them that are aloft, then they fear what they coveted, and the felicity which makes them heavy to others lies heavier on themselves: Then they praise a still quietnesse and freedome, they hate splendor, and fly from their yet unshaken state; then may you see them for feare playing the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophers; and sound counsels of a sick minde. <hi>Sen. Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st.</hi> 94.</p>
            <p n="19">(19) <hi>Which keeps in breath All virtues—Piety]</hi> Take away Piety, saith <hi>Cicero,</hi> faith also and the most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent virtue Justice is taken away. See <hi>Grot. d. jure bell. ac pac. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 20. <hi>sect.</hi> 44, 45, 46.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Ʋpon the <hi>CHORUS.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="20">(20) THe Chorus is a part of the Fable after the Act, or even before it, brought in with Musicke: Yet not only is understood by the name of Chorical what is sung; by the Quire, but also what is said by it. The Chorus is also defin'd, a part of the Fable between Act and Act. But not so aptly: because the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:205034:42"/> Chorus hath place likewise after the last Act. <hi>Scaliger</hi> defines it, <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>a part of the Fable after the Act with Musick.</hi> But the Fable also begins from the Chorus; as in <hi>Eschylus</hi>'s <hi>Persae,</hi> and <hi>Euripides</hi>'s <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus.</hi> I beleeve, because it is very unusuall; <hi>Scaliger</hi> thought that there was no regard to be had thereof. The office of the Chorus is very well expressed by <hi>Horace</hi> in <hi>Art. Poetic.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>An Actors part and office too, the Quire</l>
                  <l>Must maintain manly, not be heard to sing</l>
                  <l>Between the Acts a quite clean other thing</l>
                  <l>Then to the purpose leads, and fitly 'grees.</l>
                  <l>It still must favour good men, and to these</l>
                  <l>Be won a friend; It must both sway and bend</l>
                  <l>The angry, and love those that fear to offend.</l>
                  <l>Praise the spare diet, wholesome justice, laws,</l>
                  <l>Peace, and the open ports that peace doth cause:</l>
                  <l>Hide faults, pray to the gods, and wish aloud</l>
                  <l>Fortune would love the poor, and leave the proud.</l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>B. JONSON.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <p>The Chorus after the fifth Act was of another na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture then the former, For it often as a Judge gave sentence of those things which had bin acted; But this, as it is observed by the Greeks, so it is for the most part omitted by <hi>Seneca.</hi> The Chorus consisted of women, or men: not children, who are not enough fitted to act things; nor hath their speech that weight in comforting, admonishing, &amp;c. which are the parts of the Chorus: Sometimes it sung not, but did only speak; For when the Chorus was entred upon the Stage, it never went quite off: but, during the Play, some
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:205034:42"/> indeed went in with the Actors, the rest staid still. Lest therefore the Actors being present it should seem altogether idle, sometimes they interrupted the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, but in a few words, and when but two were talking together. If a third were present, the Chorus expected till he were gone.</p>
               <p>Thus much concerning the nature of the Greek and Latine Chorus out of <hi>Vossius</hi>'s <hi>Institut. Poetic. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 6. Whither I refer you for further instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; as likewise to my Fellow-Translator of <hi>Groti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi>'s Catechisme, in his preface to his <hi>Electra</hi> of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phocles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="21">(21) <hi>Asenath]</hi> Who was given a wife to <hi>Joseph,</hi> the daughter not indeed as many think, of the Keeper of the Prison, by name <hi>Potiphar,</hi> who bought <hi>Joseph</hi> of the Ishmaelites; (for by reason of the notorious im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modesty of his wife, he might justly have refused the daughter) but of the Priest, or rather Prince of <hi>On;</hi> that is, <hi>Heliopolis,</hi> whose name was <hi>Potiphe-rah▪ Voss. Idol. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 29. <hi>p.</hi> 210.</p>
               <p n="22">(22) <hi>From Cush] Cush</hi> was the eldest son of <hi>Cham, Gen.</hi> 10.6. From whom came the Aethiopians. The name signifies an Aethiopian or Blackamore. Some are of opinion that the curse of <hi>Noah</hi> was the cause of the blacknesse of <hi>Chams</hi> posterity.</p>
               <p n="23">(23) <hi>With noses flat, &amp;c.]</hi> A flat nose, thick lips, and a black skin is esteem'd the greatest beauty among the Aethiopians, who paint the devill white. But, how to judge of true beauty, see in one of <hi>Bacons</hi> Essaies; and in another of those, which my once School-fellow but ever honoured <hi>Samuel Gott,</hi> hath lately put forth.</p>
               <p n="24">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:205034:43"/>(24) <hi>Custome of barbarous Princes] Tacitus</hi> hath it, how that in his time the Germans almost alone of all barbarous Nations were content with single wives. Which also appeares every where in the Histories of both the Persians and Indians. <hi>Grot. d. jur. bell. &amp;c. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 5. §. 9. See likewise there, why it was not unlawfull for the Patriarks to have many wives. And how Polygamy was disliked by the wiser sort of the Heathen.</p>
               <p>Of the not onely many but incestuous marriages of the Parthians, you may read in our English <hi>Luc. l.</hi> 8.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>The Venus of those barbarous Courts who hears not?</l>
                  <l>Which like bruit beasts all wedlock rites exile,</l>
                  <l>And with wives numberlesse all Laws defile:</l>
                  <l>Th' incestuous beds abhorred secrets lie</l>
                  <l>Ope to a thousand Concubines, rais'd high</l>
                  <l>With wine and banqueting; the King refraines</l>
                  <l>No lawless lust, though ne're so full of staines, &amp;c.</l>
               </q>
               <p n="25">(25) <hi>How stands it with thy providence, &amp;c.]</hi> A weake Christian may herein be satisfied by the wise Heathen <hi>Seneca</hi>'s Answer to <hi>Lucilius</hi>'s Quaere, <hi>Why good men suffer misfortunes, seeing there is a Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence.</hi> But see likewise <hi>Grot. d. verit. Chr. Rel. l.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p n="26">(26) —Rarely known</p>
               <p>To beauty a companion.]</p>
               <p>Hee alludes to that of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venal</hi> in his tenth Satyre.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>So seldome beauty is with vertue match't.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Sir Rob: Stapylton.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <p n="27">
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:205034:43"/>(27) <hi>Who with glad hope in patience live]</hi> Because they understand all those afflictions to bee sent from God, either for chastisement of sinnes, or for exercising of their virtues, they not onely patiently but joyfully, as obedient children, receive them from the hands of a mercifull Father, and give thanks also, either for a mild correction, or an inestimable advantage. <hi>Erasm. Colloq. Epicur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="28">(28) <hi>Till the King troubled with a dream]</hi> The consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of dreames is not altogether to be rejected, which neither Physitians themselves contemne; whence there is extant a Booke of <hi>Hippocrates</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Yet this must bee done warily, lest wee mingle false things with true, which when <hi>Aristotle</hi> saw to be done of many, it made him say, that there are no divine dreames, though to him who throughly looks into that book, will appear footsteps of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary opinion. Surely the wisest sort have rightly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguish'd dreames into divine and humane. <hi>Sponda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> in <hi>Homers Ilia. l.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 63. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>On which see likewise, <hi>Plin. Epist.</hi> to <hi>Suetonius Tranquil. l.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>God revealed himselfe, and his will frequently in old times, especially before the sealing of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Canon, by dreames; sometimes even to Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, as <hi>Pharaoh, Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> &amp;c. But since the preaching of the Gospel became Oecumenicall, dreames, as also Miracles, have ceased to be of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary and familiar use: So as now, we ought rather to suspect delusion in them, then expect direction from them. Yet, although God hath now tyed us to his holy written Word, he hath no where abridged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to intimate the knowledge of his will, and the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:205034:44"/> glory of his might by dreames, miracles, &amp;c. But because the Devill may suggest dreames, and work many strange effects, which may seem Divine Revelations or Miracles, when they are nothing less, it is not safe to give easie credit to dreames, &amp;c. as Divine; Untill upon due triall there shall appear a direct tendance to the advancement of Gods glory, and a conformity unto the revealed will of God in his written Word. Moreover, so to observe our ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dreames, as to divine, or foretell of future contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, or to forecast there-from good or ill luck (as we call it) in the successe of our affaires, is a dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable superstition. Lastly, there may yet be made a lawfull, yea and a very profitable use, even of our or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary dreames; both in Physick and Divinity. Of our bodies first. For since that the predominancy of Choler, Blood, Flegme, and Melancholy; as also the differences of strength, and health, and diseases, and distempers, by diet, passion, or otherwise, cause impressions of different formes in the fancy: our dreames may help to discover both in time of health, our naturall constitution, complexion, and tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and in times of sicknesse, from the ranknesse and tyranny of which of the humors the malady sprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth. Of our soules too. For since our dreames for the most part look the same way, which our freest thoughts incline, the observing of our ordinary dreames may bee of good use for us unto that discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which of these three is our master sinne (for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one of the three every other sin is reduced) The lust of the flesh, the lust of the eyes, or the pride of life. Dr <hi>Sanderson,</hi> but more at large in his sixt Sermon, <hi>ad populum,</hi> of Gods appearing to <hi>Abimelech, Gen.</hi> 6.20.</p>
               <p n="29">
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:205034:44"/>(29) <hi>Magicians]</hi> We commonly so call them, who use diabolicall arts, and have any compact or commerce with evill spirits. That such were these, may be sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected by their successors in the time of <hi>Moses;</hi> Though the Persian <hi>Magi</hi> were Philosophers. And <hi>Cic. l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Div.</hi> The <hi>Magi</hi> are a kind of learned and wise men among the Persians. The Wise men of the East are so called, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2. The Word hath since been taken in an ill sense for Witches, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurers, and had the like fate with <hi>Tyrant, Sophister,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vossius</hi> makes three sorts of art Magicke. Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, as when an Egge moves on a Table, because of Quick-silver put into it; or a Naile hangs in the aire, because a Load-stone is hid above and beneath it. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificiall, when <hi>Archimedes</hi> burnt the Roman Ships with looking-glasses, and <hi>Archytas</hi> made a woodden Dove to fly. Daemoniacall, when a man is carried a hundred miles in an houre; a Brazen head an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers to any question, &amp;c. Which Magicke who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise, commonly joyne therewith the naturall and artificiall, that they may be thought in all the rest to wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k by nature or art.</p>
               <p n="30">(30) <hi>Heavens constellations] Theagenes</hi> foretold the Empire to <hi>Augustus. Thrasyllus</hi> shew'd what immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent danger himselfe was in from <hi>Tiberius,</hi> The Mathematicians banish'd <hi>Rome</hi> by <hi>Vitellius,</hi> foretold his death should bee before the Calends of <hi>October. Ascletarion</hi> accus'd for a Mathematician, and not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying it, boasted of what he had foreseen by his art: <hi>Domitian</hi> ask'd him if he could tell what his own end should be, and when he affirm'd that he should short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be torn of Dogs, commanded him to be slain forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:205034:45"/> and, to confute the vanity of his art, careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put into the funerall fire: which done, it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd, by a sudden tempest the pile was cast downe, and his body halfe burnt, was devoured by Dogges. The Empire was likewise foretold to <hi>Ralph</hi> of <hi>Aus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgh,</hi> and the Popedome to <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth. But it is not so hard to answer these, as is supposed. For a thing is fore-known, either by commerce with the Devill, who by reason of his subtlety and experience is seldome deceived; and often, God permitting, brings to passe what he foretels: Or when Astrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers are familiar with great men, and knowing what they go about, boast that they foreknow many things by the Stars, which they have learned elsewhere: or lastly, when crafty men among many false speake something true by chance. For that they do not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies tell truth, is proved by innumerable examples; I will now only bring in that of Pope <hi>John.</hi> 21. a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losopher, Astrologer, and Physitian, who having before his familiar friends promised himselfe long life, died the fourth moneth after. <hi>Voss. de Idolol. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 48. See also a discourse against Astrologers in <hi>Barclayes Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genis. l.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p n="31">(31) <hi>A silke white robe]</hi> White garments were worne by Princes and persons of honour among the Easterne nations, as purple among the Western. And therefore (unless I mistake) <hi>Herods</hi> souldiers arraied our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our (though mockingly) in white (for so our old Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish translations read it, with St <hi>Hierome,</hi> if the vulgar Edition be his) and <hi>Pilates</hi> in a purple robe.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="commentary">
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:205034:45"/>
            <head>Annotations upon the Second ACT.</head>
            <p n="1">(1) <hi>SOphompaneas]</hi> Is in the Originall <hi>Saphenath Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neah:</hi> which <hi>Onkelos</hi> renders, a man unto whom secrets are revealed. <hi>Jonathan,</hi> a man an Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of secrets; <hi>Josephus,</hi> a finder out of secrets. But the vulgar Latine differs from all these, which tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slates it the Saviour of the World: and that it so sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified in the Egyptian language, Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> also saith in his <hi>Quaest. Hebraic.</hi> He was called also, saith he, the Saviour of the world, because hee delivered the Land from an imminent destruction by Famine. But it is a hard matter to decide this controversie, the old Egyptian tongue being at this day almost quite lost. <hi>Voss. de Idol. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 29.</p>
            <p n="2">(2) <hi>The precious Balme] Judea</hi> abounds with fruits like ours; and besides them with the Balme and Palme. The Palme trees are tall and beautifull. The Balme is a little tree. As any bough swels, if you goe about to cut it with iron, the veines shrink back, as if afraid: they are opened with a piece of sharpe stone or shell. The juice is accounted medicinable. <hi>Tacit. Hist. l.</hi> 5.</p>
            <q>
               <p>What should I tell you of the sweating Balme From fragrant wood?</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Virg. Georg. 2,</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Upon which <hi>Servius:</hi> Balme, or Balsame is the tree it selfe: <hi>Opobalsame</hi> the juice gathered from the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:205034:46"/> tree, for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> signifies juice, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> wood: whence <hi>Xylobalsame</hi> the wood of the tree it selfe. The triall of <hi>Opobalsame</hi> (as <hi>Pliny</hi> saith) is thus: if it be held a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Sun, and be not corrupted, it will burn the hand that holds it. Some will, that war was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced to the Jewes, and <hi>Hierusalem</hi> destroyed; because they denyed to pay the tribute of balme to the Romans.</p>
            <q>
               <l>There springs the shrub three foot above the grasse,</l>
               <l>Which fears the keen edge of the Curtelace;</l>
               <l>Whereof the rich Aegyptian so endears</l>
               <l>Root, bark and fruit, &amp; much-much more the tears.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Du BARTAS.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>See <hi>Pliny, l.</hi> 12. <hi>c.</hi> 35.</p>
            <p n="3">(3) <hi>Dates like mens fingers]</hi> And therefore I suppose called <hi>Dactyli</hi> from the Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a finger.</p>
            <p n="4">(4) <hi>Spices]</hi> I follow herein our English Translation, <hi>Gen.</hi> 43.11. <hi>Grotius</hi> hath <hi>Medicinable herbs.</hi> And o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers expound the Hebrew word, Aromaticall druggs.</p>
            <p n="5">(5) <hi>Nectar of the Bees]</hi> Honey. <hi>Ovid</hi> calls milke Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctar.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Which carry Nectar in a strutting bag.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Metam. 15.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Honey prolongs life, preserves dead bodies from pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefaction; is good against the biting of a mad Dog, the sting of serpents and other poysons: good for the eyes, eares, jawes, squinsie, kernels, cough, lungs, stomach, paine in the eares, foulenesse of the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:205034:46"/> nostrils, ulcers of the mouth, blemishes of the face, clefts of the skin about the nailes of the fingers: to heale wounds, a carbuncle, boile, impostume, leprosie. <hi>Voss. de Idol. c.</hi> 79.82.3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.</p>
            <p n="6">(6) <hi>Would divine]</hi> I understand that word in a good sense. Our last English translation of the Bible hath <hi>make triall</hi> in the Margent. And <hi>Junius</hi> and <hi>Tremel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> say we should wrong so good and holy a man as <hi>Joseph</hi> was, to think he would obscure the gift recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from God of knowing secrets, and transfer the glory to himself.</p>
            <p n="7">(7) <hi>His arme which was so slow]</hi> The Divine wrath proceeds to vengeance with a loft pace, and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penceth the slownesse of the punishment with the heavinesse thereof. <hi>Val. Max.</hi> And it was a Proverbe among the wiser Heathen, that, <hi>The Gods had woollen feet, but iron hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">(8) <hi>Among men great diversity there is of manners]</hi> There is no Nation, which wholly useth the same Customes; yea there is often much difference in neighbouring Cities. But Right it selfe is equally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient for all men, and profitable both to Greeks and Barbarians. <hi>Josephus Antiq. Hist.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p n="9">(9) <hi>This Law is every where]</hi> Right reason is a law which cannot lie, nor is it a corruptible law of this or that mortall man; or a dead law written in dead bookes, or pillars, but ingraven by an immortall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in an immortall understanding. <hi>Philo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">(10) <hi>In the heart God hath it put]</hi> When the Gentiles
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:205034:47"/> which have not the Law, doe by nature the things contained in the Law: these having not the Law are a Law unto themselves; Which shew the worke of the Law written in their hearts, their conscience al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so bearing witnesse, and their thoughts in the meane while accusing or else excusing one another, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14, 15.</p>
            <p n="11">(11) <hi>Mercy alone man nigh to God doth make] Antoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> to <hi>Faustina:</hi> There is nothing can better com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend a Roman Emperor to Nations than Clemency. This made <hi>Caesar</hi> a God, this consecrated <hi>Augustus.</hi> And <hi>Themist. in orat.</hi> Whereas there be three things which make God to bee God; Eternity of life, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightinesse of power, and uncessantly to do good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men: in this last onely can a King come to be like God. The most wise City of <hi>Athens</hi> took mercy not for an affection but a Deity, saith <hi>Fab. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 11. <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menius</hi> makes mention of an Altar there built to Mercy. How much also the Romans esteem'd thereof appeares, in that they, and especially the latter wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are wont to honour Clemency with the name of Piety.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Be pious above all things: onely we,</l>
               <l>Unlike else, are like Gods in Clemency.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Claudian.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ss. Instit. Orat. l. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>153. See like wise</hi> Grot. de jur. bel. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">(12) <hi>Such hath bin and such is the custome]</hi> But if those Lawes of men are unjust, which kill the children for the parents fault; certainely much more unjust was the Law of the Persians and Macedonians, which put
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:205034:47"/> to death their kindred, to the end they who had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended the King might perish more sad, as <hi>Curtius</hi> speaks, <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>Grot. de jur. bel. &amp;c. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 25.</p>
            <p n="13">(13) <hi>Five Families]</hi> I did not at the first fully under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand the Authors meaning. But afterwards I found in his Book <hi>de jur. bel. &amp;c.</hi> a note that gives light to this very place. <hi>viz Philo</hi> saith, It was the custome for tyrants to destroy with the parties condemned the five next Families to them. <hi>Grot. ut supra, in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notat.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Ʋpon the <hi>CHORUS.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="14">(14) <hi>PHaenicia]</hi> A Countrey of <hi>Asia</hi> neer unto <hi>Judea,</hi> whose chiefe Cities were <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon. Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sephus</hi> writes, that they first invented the Greek Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; and <hi>Strabo,</hi> that they were famous for arts of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation and war.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Phaenix</hi> was the same with <hi>Esau</hi> or <hi>Edom,</hi> thus <hi>Vossius:</hi> The Erythraeans are from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, red; <hi>Ery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thea,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, rednesse. And the Erythraean sea tooke this name from King <hi>Erythras,</hi> as the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles call him, who in the Scriptures is <hi>Esau,</hi> or <hi>Edom,</hi> that is, red. They differ only in language; therefore the Hebrew, <hi>Edoms,</hi> or <hi>Idumean</hi> sea, the Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and the Latine <hi>Mare rubrum,</hi> or red sea. But if the Tyrians came from the Idumaean sea; the reason is not obscure, why they are called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. For <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> are the same. And <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the same with <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, red: And therefore the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:205034:48"/> Latines of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> have made <hi>puniceus:</hi> as from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Paenus,</hi> whence <hi>Punicus.</hi> But that the Tyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans came from the Idumaean sea, <hi>Pliny</hi> and <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus</hi> say: <hi>Herodotus</hi> also, and <hi>Strabo,</hi> and <hi>Proco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">(15) <hi>Taauta]</hi> Perhaps I should say <hi>Taautas.</hi> I tooke it for the name of a Towne in <hi>Phaenicia.</hi> But I finde in <hi>Vossius:</hi> That <hi>Taautus</hi> invented the art of writing, and was the first who left behind him Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of things done: and was by the Aegyptians cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Thoor,</hi> or rather <hi>Thoud,</hi> by the Alexandrians <hi>Thoth,</hi> by the Grecians <hi>Hermes,</hi> the same with <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">(16) <hi>In twice twelve letters]</hi> The common opinion both of our men, and the Hebrews was, that <hi>Moses</hi> was the Author of the Hebrew letters, which is as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serted by <hi>Eupolemus, Artapanus,</hi> and other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane writers, who report that <hi>Moses</hi> was a wise man, and the Inventor of letters, which he delivered to the Jewes, from whom the neighbouring Phaeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians receiv'd them, from the Phaenicians the Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians by <hi>Cadmus.</hi> Moreover, the same <hi>Artapanus</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves that <hi>Moses</hi> gave the Aegyptians letters, and is that <hi>Mercury,</hi> whom wee find among all the Greek and Latine Writers to have taught that Nation let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. But if any aske, in what letters then the wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Egyptians was contained, wherein wee read that <hi>Moses</hi> was learned, perhaps hee will find, it was only wont to be delivered and taught by word of mouth, and preserv'd in the memory of the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and learners▪ and that the forms of letters, if there were any then, were images of living Creatures
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:205034:48"/> which they call'd Hieroglyphicks. <hi>Philo Judaeus</hi> as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribes the Invention of Letters to <hi>Abraham:</hi> but they seeme to have been many yeeres before <hi>Abraham.</hi> For <hi>Josephus</hi> 1 <hi>Antiq.</hi> tels us, That by the sonnes of <hi>Seth</hi> the son of <hi>Adam</hi> were erected two pillars, one of stone, the other of brick, and that the Arts which they had invented, were written on them, of which that of stone remain'd in <hi>Syria</hi> even in his time. <hi>Viv. in Aug. de. Civ. Dei. l.</hi> 18. <hi>c.</hi> 39.</p>
               <p n="17">(17) <hi>Crocodile] Voss. de. Idol. l.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1027. The Crocodile is eighteen foot long. It is bred out of an egge no big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then a goose egge. Nor is there any other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (as <hi>Pliny</hi> saith) which from a lesser beginning growes to a greater magnitude. Yea, as he adds af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, some thinke that this one Creature growes as long as it lives. <hi>p.</hi> 1034. The Crocodile hath an exceeding great force in the taile; with the stroke whereof it breakes the legges even of a strong foure-footed beast.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Voss.</hi> out of <hi>Plin.</hi> The eye-teeth of a Crocodile drives away agues, if you fill them with frankincense (for they are hollow) so that the sicke party see not him in five daies who shall have bound them unto him. They say that the little stones taken out of her belly are good against the shaking fits of an ague.</p>
               <p>They are wont, as <hi>Herodotus</hi> in <hi>Euterpe</hi> hath it, to take Crocodiles in this manner. They put a hooke into a chine of Pork which the hunter casts into a Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: Then standing on the banke, he beats a live Pig, whose cry the Crocodile hearing comes on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pace, and lighting upon the chine of Pork devoures it with the hook; and is forthwith drawn upon the bank; and because so also he will bee troublesome enough,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:205034:49"/> they fill his eyes with mud, that hee may not see what the hunter does. <hi>Voss. p</hi> 1134.</p>
               <p>Some say, that Crocodiles weep, because their teares are become a proverbe. But this is meant of feigned teares not true: nor is it cleare enough what truth there is under that fable of the feigned tears of a Crocodile.</p>
               <p>The Crocodile also is made to have speech by the Stoicks in their Sophisme which they call <hi>Croco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dilites.</hi> But this is to bee put among <hi>Aesops</hi> Fables. For as <hi>Pliny</hi> saith, This one terrestriall creature wants the use of a tongue. <hi>Idem. p</hi> 978.</p>
               <p n="18">(18) <hi>To death a new way showes]</hi> There is a Booke of <hi>Dicaearchus, concerning the destruction of men,</hi> who having collected all other causes, as deluge, pestilence, desolation, also sudden multiplying of wild beasts, by whose incursion he shews, that some people have been consumed, compares then, how many more men have been destroyed by the invasion of men, that is, by wars, or seditions, then by any other calamity. <hi>Cic. de offic. l.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p n="19">(19) <hi>Purple by Kings to be worne]</hi> The purple colour at this day is not from the liquor of the shell-fish call'd a Purple, but from herbs. In times past the water and fishes had this honour. Whence Saint <hi>Ambrose Hexam. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 2. What should I speake also of the Purples which furnish the tables and the the garments of Kings? What is adored in Kings, is from the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>Voss. l.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 1463.</p>
               <p n="20">(20) <hi>The Emerald]</hi> Emeralds of all precious stones are most pleasing to the sight in regard nothing is greener
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:205034:49"/> which you can compare with them. They onely of all gemmes take up the eye and not satisfie it. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, the sight wearied with being intentive upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things is recreated by an Emerald. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they who cut jewels refresh their wearinesse with this most delightful greenness. <hi>Perot.</hi> upon <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial. p.</hi> 248.</p>
               <p n="21">(21) <hi>To a thin plank hath</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our precious lives taught to commit]</hi> It was said by one, that there was but an inch board between Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and death. And <hi>Cato</hi> repented him, that ever he went by water, when he might have gone by Land.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Rash man was he with ships fraile beake</l>
                  <l>Did first the treacherous billows break.</l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Senec. Med.</hi> Englished by <hi>E.S.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <p n="22">(22) <hi>O happy the first Age]</hi> How well what the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets have fabled of the golden Age, agrees with the state of man in Paradise! as I doubt not, but they had these things from tradition. Surely the first age of man in the Poets is the same with the first in the Scriptures: And <hi>Saturne</hi> the same with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam. Voss.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what Poets write of the golden Age is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne. Hear what an Orator saith of it and them. <q>—<hi>That happy and as we call it golden Age was bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren of Orators and crimes, but abounded with Poets and Prophets.</hi>
                     <bibl> Quintil. Dialog. de Orat.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="23">
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:205034:50"/>(23) <hi>A simple life, chast enough though naked]</hi> That the first life of man was with simplicity and naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, the Egyptians also taught; whence the Poets golden Age, celebrated even by the Indians, as <hi>Strabo</hi> hath it, <hi>Grot. de ver. Rel. l.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p n="24">(24) A coat became A covering to hide our shame]</p>
               <p>After that the woman deceiv'd by the Serpent, had drawne her husband to partake of her sinne, their eyes indeed were open'd, but so as that they saw themselves to be destitute of a covering, not only of a coat, but also of virtue. <hi>Voss. de Idol. l.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p n="25">(25) <hi>With such a noise as Nile downe flowes]</hi> Where <hi>Nilus</hi> fals downe headlong from those most high Mountaines at those places which are call'd the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taracts; the people that inhabit thereabouts, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the greatnesse of the noise want the sense of hearing. <hi>Cic. in Somn. Scip.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Nor that which Nilus falling water makes</l>
                  <l>Precipitated down the Cataracts,</l>
                  <l>When with his fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m he seems to lave the skie,</l>
                  <l>And strikes a deafnesse through the dwellers nigh.</l>
                  <bibl>Continuation of <hi>Luc.</hi> Book 3.</bibl>
               </q>
               <p n="26">(26) <hi>The son laugh'd at his Fathers shame]</hi> The anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Bacchus</hi> is no other then <hi>Noah.</hi> For hee first planted a Vineyard, and taught how to make wine, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.20. Nor are there wanting learned men, who suppose, that the very name of <hi>Bacchus</hi> makes for this opinion. For they will have from <hi>Noach Noa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> hence <hi>Nachus,</hi> thence <hi>Bachus,</hi> then <hi>Bacchus.</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:205034:50"/> But though I think <hi>Bacchus</hi> to be worshipped in <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> Yet I like not so forc'd an Etymology, especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whereas the Greeks seem not to have said <hi>Noa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h</hi> but <hi>Noe. Voss de Idol. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 19.</p>
               <p>Of <hi>Noah</hi> supplanted by wine, thus <hi>Du Bartas.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Oppress'd with sleep he wallowes on the ground,</l>
                  <l>His shamelesse snorting trunk so deeply drown'd</l>
                  <l>In selfe oblivion, that he did not hide</l>
                  <l>Those parts, which Caesar cover'd when he di'd.</l>
               </q>
               <p n="27">(27) <hi>The Daughter to her Father brought a Grandchild—] Lot's</hi> Daughters; of whom likewise <hi>D. Bartas.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Within your wombs you bear for nine moneths time,</l>
                  <l>The upbraiding burden of your shamelesse crime;</l>
                  <l>And troubling kindreds names and natures quite,</l>
                  <l>You both became even in one very night</l>
                  <l>Wives to your fathers, sisters to your sons,</l>
                  <l>And mothers to your brothers all at once.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="commentary">
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:205034:51"/>
            <head>Annotations upon the Third ACT.</head>
            <p n="1">(1) <hi>REd Sea]</hi> The Sea, with which that [Land] is washed, differs not from others in colour, the name is given it from King <hi>Erythras</hi> [which signifies red] and therefore ignorant people believe that the waters are red. <hi>Curtius l.</hi> 8. See the note upon <hi>Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2) <hi>Bread by a griping hand was sold]</hi> There is no op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression and exaction, saith <hi>Gregory Naz anzen</hi> at the funerall of <hi>Basil,</hi> more harsh and heavy, then of those who watch for hard times, that they may have the better trading in a dearth, and make a harvest out of others calamity. <hi>Tiberius</hi> is rather to be imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, who (as it is in <hi>Tacitus</hi>) the people complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a dearth of corne, set downe a price for the the buyer, promising to pay of his owne in every bushell<note n="*" place="bottom">3. <hi>ob. q.</hi> Sir <hi>H. S.</hi>
               </note> two <hi>nummos. Aerodius rerum judicat. l.</hi> 9. <hi>tit. de annona c.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p n="3">(3) <hi>Sacred Ibis]</hi> Of worshipping the Ibis [a Bird in <hi>Aegypt</hi>] not only <hi>Lucian,</hi> but <hi>Cic. l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Nat. deor. &amp; Tusc.</hi> 5. Also <hi>Javen. Sat.</hi> 15. make mention. <hi>Plin. l.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 28. saith: <hi>The Aegyptians invocate their Ibes against the approach of Serpents.</hi> The same cause of divine honour <hi>Herodotus</hi> gives in <hi>Euterpe,</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:205034:51"/> where also he describes them, and saith, <hi>It was a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall crime among the Aegyptians for any one to kill an Ibis, or Hawke, whether knowingly, or ignorantly.</hi> Vos. l. 4. p 1274.</p>
            <p>The Ibis drinks not of foule water or infected with poyson, but pure and wholesome: and this is said to be the cause, why, as <hi>Aelian</hi> saith, <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>de animal. c.</hi> 45. <hi>the Priests in Aegypt sprinkle not themselves with any water, but with that which they believe the Ibis to have drank of.</hi> Voss.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Herodotus</hi> is Author, that other Nations had the use of a clyster from the Egyptians: So <hi>Galen</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth that the Egyptians lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ned it from the <hi>Ibis.</hi> And before him, thus <hi>Pliny: With the hooked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of their beak they purge themselves in that part, out of which it is most wholesome to cast the burden of our meat.</hi> Voss l. 3. p. 1258.</p>
            <p n="4">(4) <hi>Asps]</hi> Infuse not (as some say) poyson with their taile, but, like other serpents, having made a wound with their saw-like teeth, they breath it thereinto out of small holes underneath, wherein a little skin they keep it for those uses: Whence of Detractors, <hi>Psal.</hi> 140. <hi>The poyson of Aspes is under their lips. Cleopatra</hi> chose the biting of an Aspe, as an easier kind of death then to drinke poyson, or fall upon a sword. For it is so little the Aspe hurts, as it cannot be felt, nor so much as the pricke of a needle be seen, which lessens the griefe, whereas the greater wounds are wont to have the greater pain. The pain is also lesse lasting, because of a poyson,
<q>
                  <l>Which in no Serpent is compacted more.</l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Luc. l. 9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:205034:52"/>
            <p>A most piercing poyson therefore, saith <hi>Aelian,</hi> and penetrating most swiftly; which is the cause, why, whereas it comes so speedily to the heart, it also ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stens death. This is done sooner by the females then the males; because the males have but two teeth, the females foure. But though the wound bee so little, there comes a little blood out, and that discolour'd, who are stricken live not above foure houres. Yet, such is the divine goodnesse, they are curable by drinking of vinegar; which was first found out by a Boy, who being bitten by an Aspe, and extreame thirsty, for want of water at hand dranke often of a vinegar bottle which he carried, and by that meanes recovered. See <hi>Plin.</hi> and <hi>Celsus,</hi> cited by <hi>Voss. l.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 1515.</p>
            <p n="5">(5) <hi>When the shady night]</hi> I suppose our Author al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes to a place in <hi>Tacit. Annal. l.</hi> 1 There was one <hi>Percennius</hi>— Who after the better sort were gone to their lodgings, by little and little in secret con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles in the night, or in the shutting of the eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning gathered together, and stirred up the unexper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test of the Souldiers, and such as were most doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full what entertainment they should expect after the death of <hi>Augustus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Englished by Sir</hi> H. Savile.</p>
            <p n="6">(6) <hi>The mother bear her child againe]</hi> Such horrid ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Famine wee read in <hi>Josephus</hi> at the siege of <hi>Hierusalem.</hi> Our Author in his <hi>Christus Patiens</hi> makes <hi>Joseph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea</hi> wish them (Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally) to the Jewes for crucifying our Saviour. An example hereof we have likewise (to omit prophane Histories) in the siege of <hi>Samaria,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 6.29.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:205034:52"/> Wherein was fulfilled what the Divine vengeance threatneth to a disobedient people, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.53. <hi>The hands of the pittifull women have sodden their own children, they were their meat,</hi> Lam. 4.10. See <hi>Lips. d. Const. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 23. <hi>Hackwel's Apolog. l.</hi> 2. §. 4. <hi>Fox. Martyrol. vol.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 482. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1314.</p>
            <p n="7">(7) <hi>Coptos]</hi> The Antiquity of this City wee know by this, that Queen <hi>Isis</hi> here heard the newes of the death of her husband <hi>Osiris,</hi> and for griefe cut off her haire. Whence the Greeks think the City took the name of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, because <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> signifies to cut. But others imagine the City hath the name from the Aegyptian word <hi>Copti,</hi> which signifies pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: because <hi>Isis</hi> when she lived there, was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd of her husband. Of both which <hi>Plutarch. Voss. l.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 617. In <hi>Diripitur ardens Coptos</hi> our Author imitates <hi>Senec. in Troad. Diripitur ardens Troia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">(8) <hi>The battering Ram]</hi> An Engine us'd in War, of which <hi>Cic. d. Offic. l.</hi> 1. They who laying downe their armes shall come out upon the faith of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, though the Ram have batter'd the wall, are to be receiv'd.</p>
            <p n="9">(9) <hi>The creeping Vine]</hi> An Engine, under which souldiers safely hid came to undermine the wals of a Towne. Whereof <hi>Lucan l.</hi> 3.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Then did a thin earth cover'd work proceed,</l>
               <l>Under whose covert those that lay did fall</l>
               <l>To work in undermining of the wall.</l>
               <l>Sometimes the back forc'd Ram did strongly drive</l>
               <l>Forward, the well compacted wall to rive. <bibl>
                     <hi>T. M.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p n="10">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:205034:53"/>(10) <hi>Nabataeans]</hi> A people of the East, of whom <hi>Ovid:</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>The East wind to Aurora tooke his flight</l>
                  <l>And Nabataean Kingdoms—</l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Metam. 1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>They are so called from <hi>Nebaioth</hi> the eldest sonne of <hi>Ishmael. Gen.</hi> 25.13.</p>
            <p n="11">(11) <hi>Alive them bury in the Mines]</hi> We descend into the entrailes of the earth, we go down as far as to the seat and habitation of the infernall spirits, and all to meet with rich treasure, &amp;c. <hi>Plin. l.</hi> 33. <hi>in Proaem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will not dispute it, whether all minerals were made at the first creation, or have since received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease by tract of time, which latter I confesse I ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>Quercetan</hi> incline unto, they being some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of the nature of stones, which undoubtedly grow, though not by augmentation or accretion, yet by assimilation or apposition, turning the neighbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring earth into their substance; Yet thus much may we confidently affirme, that the Minerals themselves wast not in the ordinary course, but by the insatiable desire of mankinde. Nay, such is the <hi>Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence,</hi> that even there, where they are most vex'd and wrought upon, yet are they not worn out, not wasted in the <hi>whole.</hi> Of late within these few yeers <hi>Mendip</hi> Hils yeelded, I think, more lead then ever; and at this day I do not hear that the Iron Mines in <hi>Sussex,</hi> or the Tin works in <hi>Cornwall</hi> are any whit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated; which I confesse to be somewhat strange, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering this little corner furnishes in a manner all the Christian world with that mettall. Dr <hi>Hackwels Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, l.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p n="12">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:205034:53"/>(12) <hi>I'le to my faithfull wife (within) relate]</hi> Our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor makes <hi>Sophompaneas</hi> a good and loving husband, and endued with virtues, not onely politicall but Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conomicall. Wherein he doth indeed present to you the perfect Idea of a worthy Magistrate, who ought (with the Apostles Bishop, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.4.) to be one that ruleth well his own house.</p>
            <p n="13">(13) —<hi>With an equall patience hear Both sides.]</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Who, th' other side unheard, makes a Decree,</l>
               <l>Although it may be just, yet unjust he.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Sen. Medea.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p n="14">(14) <hi>A heavenly spirit doth, within, him teach]</hi> For he was most skilfull in prodigies, and the first that found out the interpretation of dreames, nor did any thing of divine or humane law seem unknown to him: in so much as that he foresaw a dearth many yeeres before, and all <hi>Aegypt</hi> had perished unlesse by his admonition the King had commanded corn to be laid up for many yeers, and his experiments were so great, as that his answers seem'd to be given not by a man, but from God. <hi>Justin. l.</hi> 36.</p>
            <p n="15">(15) <hi>Twelve signes]</hi> Astrologers have divided the Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diacke into twelve signes and no more; because the Sunne whilest it goes circuit is in conjunction twelve times with the Moone, and they have distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted every signe into 30 degrees, because the Moon in thirty daies is again in conjunction with the Sunne, whence also it is clear, why there be 360 degrees, for as much as they come to so many, if you reckon 12 times thirty. <hi>Voss. l.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 568.</p>
            <p n="16">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:205034:54"/>(16) <hi>In dreames by night]</hi> Of divine dreames see <hi>Num.</hi> 12 6. <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.17. Examples thereof in the old Testament, the dreame of <hi>Abraham, Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech, Jacob, Laban, Joseph, Pharaoh, Solomon, Nabuchodonosor, Dan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el, &amp;c.</hi> And in the New, of <hi>Joseph,</hi> the <hi>Magi, Pilates</hi> wife, <hi>Paul.</hi> Whereby is abundantly confuted the opinion of <hi>Aristotle,</hi> when he proves that no dreames are from God, because it would be absurd to send them, not to the best and wisest, but to the simpler sort: For that they were nor only sent to the simple and unskilfull, the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples alledg'd sufficiently teach. But <hi>Aristotle</hi> was deceiv'd, in that the dreames which the Gentiles boasted for divine, were for the most part of vulgar men. Indeed the Devill could more easily abuse the more simple and credulous. But the forenamed were almost a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l men famous for wisdome and holinesse, yea many of them in high dignity. Whence also is refelled that he thought all divinations introduc'd by lawes to be the better observ'd by the people. Some defend <hi>Aristotle</hi> herein, in that God would rather teach m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n waking then sleeping, and in open words then in dreames for the most part obscure. But God would instruct us by more then one way. Besides therefore the ordinary manner wherein by reading or hearing his word he certifies us concerning heavenly Mysteries and his will; hee would also use another way, whereby he makes us partakers of his secrets even neither seeing nor hearing. Moreover, it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest that the minde of man is more fit in his sleep to receive heavenly things, because it is then void and free from earthly cares. And when he awakes &amp; ruminates on the dream, the darknesse and silence of the night breed a greater veneration towards Divine things.
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:205034:54"/> Surely the night is fit for the meditation of weighty matters. Yea this also addes to the veneration, that the dreames were not alwaies plaine: By which meanes men were withall stirr'd up to seek the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding of them from God or godly men. So that this also was an argument of the Divine good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, that sometimes he would send dreames even to Heathen Kings; but the interpretation whereof they should fetch not from Magicians but from holy men: as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> from <hi>Joseph, Nabuchodonosor</hi> from <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el.</hi> For hereby God invited both the Kings and their wise men, yea all their subjects to an acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the coelestiall and true Deity, and to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance from their sins. <hi>Voss. Idolol. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 35.</p>
            <p n="17">(17) <hi>In a treble ring] Aegypt</hi> was divided into six se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall sorts of people. The three first, which were Kings, Priests, and souldiers, govern'd the State and Common-wealth of <hi>Aegypt:</hi> The other three ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the Country to use things necessary for the Kingdom and state, which were Husbandmen, crafts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and shepherds. <hi>Diod. Sic.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">(18) —<hi>Astrange sight to tread</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Meale with their feet, clay with their hands to knead.]</hi> I suppose <hi>Grotius</hi> meanes Bakers, and Bricke-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, or Potters. And I finde in <hi>Joan. Aubanus</hi> (a German Geographer) who, I believe hath it out of <hi>Diodorus Siculus,</hi> That (among other strange cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes) the Egyptians did use to make bread with their feet and clay with their hands.</p>
            <p n="19">(19) —<hi>Whether the North Star doth stay</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ever at the same distance fom the Pole.]</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:205034:55"/>
            <p>The Poets fable that the seventh Star of the Pleiades by name <hi>Electra,</hi> after the Destruction of <hi>Troy</hi> would no more be seen: because <hi>Dardanus</hi> the founder of the Trojan Nation was born of <hi>Electra.</hi> And, that I may the more easily pardon the heathen poets, there have not been wanting in our age, who thought, that the Polar star hath in like manner hid it selfe after the taking of <hi>Constantinople;</hi> than which nothing is more vaine. For if you except a little one which lies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Pole and <hi>Ursa minor,</hi> that very same in the taile of <hi>Ursa minor,</hi> as it was of old in the time of <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parcus</hi> and <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> is also at this day most neere the Pole, and in like manner is called the Polar Starre. <hi>Voss.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">(20) <hi>Why Heaven brings forth new starres]</hi> But, say they, if Heaven be either watery, or airy, or starres fiery; both are of an Elementall nature; and so liable to generation and corruption: which the experience of so many ages contradicts; seeing no alteration hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto is made either in the magnitude or number or brightnesse of the stars. Which when they say they little thinke that they give judgement of a body so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from our senses; where innumerable mutations may be, unto which the edge of our eyes cannot reach. For it is as if from Heaven wee should con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template earth; whose magnitude and form would alwaies seem the same to us, however singulars are subject to corruption. Moreover, their opinion is cleerly refel'd by new stars which at divers times have appear'd in Heaven. As that mention'd by <hi>Pliny, l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 26. Another in the time of <hi>Adrian</hi> the Emperor. Another under <hi>Otho</hi> 1. Another in the Yeere 1264. And what shall wee say to that in the Yeere 1572?
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:205034:55"/> Which to have truly been in the firmament, <hi>Clavius</hi> proves by a double argument: one, because it was seen by all men from most divers parts of <hi>Europe</hi> in the same place of <hi>Cassiopea:</hi> the other, that as long as it lasted (which was almost two yeeres) it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly followed the motion not of one Planet, but of the fixt stars. Now that it was a new star, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver before seen, all the Mathematicians thought, except <hi>Annibal Raimund</hi> of <hi>Verona.</hi> Wherefore wee must conclude, that this new star was of coelestiall matter, but not wrought so solidly, and unto perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity as others are wont, which because more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact, are so much more perfect, and not so dissolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And even at this day an empty space is there seen, where that star first appear'd. I dispute not whether it shin'd with its owne light, or the light of the Sun. It is enough, that the matter thereof was not carryed up thither from the earth. For how should it be elevated above the Sun it selfe? In what mannner likewise could so grosse a matter exhale out of the globe of the earth, and that three hundred times bigger then the globe of the Earth and Water? For such was the magnitude of that star at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; what shall I say of other stars afterwards in like manner, in the judgement of Mathematicians, bred in the skie? as of that in the yeere 1577, which appear'd seven weekes: of which another in 1600: another in 1604. And surely whether it were a star or a comet in the yeer 1618. all good Astrologers plac'd it in heaven. <hi>Voss. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 39.</p>
            <p n="21">(21) <hi>See you those figures written in the dust]</hi> The old Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians much exercised themselves in Geometry, Arithmeticke, Astronomy; Geometry they studied
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:205034:56"/> of necessity, because when the bounds of their fields were removed by the o'reflowing of <hi>Nilus,</hi> after the River was returned into it's channel, every one was to have their owne restor'd again: nor could the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of grounds be otherwise assigned then by apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an art, which made up out of certaine principles, could not deceive skilfull measurers. And it was therefore called Geometry, as it were a measuring of the Earth. Now they gave themselves to Astrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my by reason of the commodity thereof, as who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving alwaies cleare nights, and beholding the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Heaven far and wide, troubled with no clouds nor mists, could easily observe the rising and setting, the progresse and regresse of the stars, which was most pleasant to know and profitable for life, and worthy the exercise of mans wit: then also to these two Geometry and Astrology was added, that as it were subservient, and whose ministery these cannot bee without, the knowledge of numbers which is called Arithmeticke. <hi>Viv. in Aug. de Civ. Dei, l.</hi> 18. <hi>c.</hi> 39.</p>
            <p n="22">(22) <hi>Hieroglyphicke]</hi> The Aegyptian Priests in stead of letters did use figures of all sorts of creatures, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which they cleerly express'd their conceptions. <hi>Plutarch l. de Iside &amp; Osiride.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>The rivers yet had not with paper serv'd</l>
               <l>Aegypt, but carv'd beasts, birds and stones preserv'd</l>
               <l>Their Magick language. <bibl>
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> l. <hi>3. May.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p n="23">(23) <hi>Pyramids]</hi> The Pyramids are worthy wonder and amazement by reason of their magnitude. Some are reported to have been so high, as all did greatly admire
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:205034:56"/> how the cement could be carried up. They say that one of them was twenty yeers in building by 360000 men. That there was no other cause of building them, then a vain ostentation of the wealth of the Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Kings: either lest the leaving money to their suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors might be an occasion of treason against them, or that the people should not be idle. There were three between <hi>Memphis</hi> and <hi>Delta,</hi> whereof two are reckon'd the wonders of the World. The third is lesse, but cost more. The lower halfe is of that blacke stone whereof mortars are made. Under this some say, <hi>Rhodope</hi> is buried, one of whose shoos, whil'st she was washing, an Eagle took up, and let fall in the lap of an Egyptian King. Which hee admiring caus'd her to be sought out, and married her. And, when she was dead, built this Pyramis over her. They are so cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> fire, which is broad at bottome, and sharp in the top. Their Kings were buried under them. <hi>Perot. Cornucop. in Martial.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="24">(24) <hi>A business of great moment]</hi> All Monopolies are not repugnant to the law of nature: For they may sometimes be permitted by the supreme power upon a just cause, and at a set rate. Whereof wee have an il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lustrious example in the history of <hi>Joseph,</hi> when hee was the Kings Vicegerent in <hi>Aegypt. Grot. de Jur. bel. &amp;c. l.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 235.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:205034:57"/>
               <head>Ʋpon the <hi>CHORUS.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="25">(25) <hi>NIle or if Siris] Nilus</hi> is in the Scriptures cal'd by a double name: one common; the other more proper. The common appellation is the river of <hi>Aegypt, Gen.</hi> 15.18. which in Hebrew is <hi>Nachal Mitzraim.</hi> Now for <hi>Nahal</hi> or <hi>Naal,</hi> the Syrians and Egyptians say <hi>Neel;</hi> as the Phaenicians and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for <hi>Bahal</hi> or <hi>Baal, Beel;</hi> and as from <hi>Beel Bel,</hi> thence <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, so from <hi>Neel Nel,</hi> whence <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The other name in the Scripture is <hi>Sichor, Isa.</hi> 23.3. <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.18. which signifies blacke. For <hi>Scachar</hi> is <hi>to be made blacke.</hi> Whence the old Latin word <hi>scurus,</hi> and with a praeposition, <hi>obscurus.</hi> For the water of <hi>Nile</hi> is thicke and blackish, by reason of the mud it brings with it from the South parts. It makes also the land black in moistening it: as the haires of young men are blacke by reason of moisture, which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards through defect thereof grow hoary. And what if we say that <hi>Osiris</hi> is from <hi>Sihor</hi> or <hi>Sior?</hi> For <hi>Sior,</hi> the letters transpos'd, is <hi>Osir,</hi> whence, adding the Greeke and Latine termination, <hi>Osiris.</hi> And from <hi>Osiris</hi> they said <hi>Siris.</hi> For so the Ethiopians and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians call <hi>Nilus. Voss. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 74.</p>
               <p n="26">(26) <hi>With our parents</hi>] The Ethiopians. By whom <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> was also called <hi>Astapus,</hi> which, in their language, signifies water breaking out of darknesse, and which likewise on the left side where the streame fals is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:205034:57"/>
                  <hi>Astabores,</hi> &amp; on the right side <hi>Astusabes,</hi> and not <hi>Nilus</hi> before they meet in one full River. <hi>Plin. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p n="27">(27) <hi>What shall I say</hi>—] Our Author I suppose al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes to a discourse after supper between <hi>Caesar,</hi> and the old Aegyptian Priest <hi>Achoreus,</hi> concerning the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall of <hi>Nilus,</hi> in the last Booke of <hi>Lucan.</hi> Which may serve for a Comment upon this whole Chorus, and is worth your reading, but too long to bee tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scrib'd hither by me. See likewise <hi>Seneca l.</hi> 4. <hi>Natural. Quaest. c.</hi> 2. <hi>Farnab. in Lucan. l.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p n="28">(28) <hi>It had no need of raine from Heaven</hi>] Whosoever shall consider the benefits of <hi>Nilus,</hi> he will cease to wonder, that <hi>Water</hi> was by no Nations had in greater honour, then among the Egyptians. For without <hi>Nilus</hi> what would all <hi>Egypt</hi> be? Seeing its soile is nitrous, and parch'd with the Sunne, and almost as hard as any stone; in many places also gaping so, as that a Horse-man cannot travell; nor is this evill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medied by raine, which <hi>Aegypt</hi> knowes not, if you except <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and other places nigh the Sea. But <hi>Nilus</hi> is to the Egyptian soile in stead of raine from heaven: whereupon, not <hi>Ovid</hi> indeed, as <hi>L. Seneca l.</hi> 4. <hi>Nat. Quaest. c.</hi> 2. his memory flip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, relates; but his contemporary <hi>Tibullies</hi> hath sung:
<q>
                     <l>Thou art the cause, thy land doth beg no rain,</l>
                     <l>Nor the dry grass for showres to <hi>Jove</hi> complaine.</l>
                     <bibl>l <hi>1.</hi> el. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:205034:58"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Parmeno</hi> also of <hi>Byzantium</hi> hath it in <hi>Athaeneus, O Nile the Aegyptian Jupiter.</hi> Wherefore it is by <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, l. de profugis,</hi> said to be <hi>onely not a corrivall of Heaven.</hi> Yea <hi>Heliodorus</hi> in his ninth Booke saith ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly, that it is called by the Egyptians <hi>the corrivall of Heaven:</hi> and he addes the reason, because with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out raine it waters, and moistens as it were with a showre. This is the first benefit of <hi>Nilus.</hi> But it would bee a small thing, that a nitrous and barren soile should be water'd. By the Divine Providence therefore another benefit is, that when it ebbes, it leaves the grounds not only softned, but also mudded: as it is in <hi>Cic.</hi> 2. <hi>de Nat. Deor.</hi> And more fully there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>Seneca, l.</hi> 4. <hi>Quaest. Nat. c.</hi> 2. <hi>Nilus</hi> on a sandy and thirsty soile brings both water and earth. For whereas it flowes troubled and foule, it leaves all the dreggs in the dry and gaping places, and daubes up the chinkes with whatsoever fat is carried along with it: and is profitable to the grounds for two causes, both that it overflowes, and that it bemires them. <hi>Vos. de Idolol. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 75.</p>
               <p n="29">(29) <hi>Eight Cubits</hi>] The fertility of <hi>Aegypt</hi> is according to the increase of <hi>Nilus:</hi> whence <hi>Pliny, lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Hist. cap.</hi> 9. At twelve cubits a famine followes, at thirteen there will yet be a dearth; fourteen make the Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans merry, fifteen secure, sixteen luxurious. <hi>Voss. l.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 216.</p>
               <p n="30">(30) <hi>The Dog star</hi>] As among the Planets the star of <hi>Venus,</hi> which we call <hi>Phosphorus,</hi> and <hi>Hesperus,</hi> so among the fixed stars the Dog-star was the first which had Divine honours given it. Yea it was prefer'd by the Egyptians before <hi>Hesperus,</hi> and called
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:205034:58"/>
                  <hi>Isis,</hi> which with <hi>Osiris</hi> is their chiefe Deity. This star is so bright above other stars, as that if you lay a looking-glasse upon the water you may see it at noon day; yea, who are sharpe sighted may see it or thinke they see it, even without a glasse. <hi>Voss. l.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 498.</p>
               <p>The Dog-star is called <hi>Sirius</hi> from <hi>Siris;</hi> because of the great conspiracy between the Dog-starre and <hi>Nilus.</hi> For in the dog-daies <hi>Nilus</hi> doth most of all overflow; as that in like manner both the Dog in Heaven, and <hi>Nilus</hi> rageth in earth. <hi>Idem, p.</hi> 692.</p>
               <p n="31">(31) <hi>Her raine into thy river powre] Nilus</hi> begins to increase by and by after the Solitice about the fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of <hi>June.</hi> The cause whereof are the perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all showrs nigh the Equinoctiall line: where it is Winter, when it is Summer with them, who dwell under the Tropicke of <hi>Cancer,</hi> and on this side of it. With these showers therefore rushing in heapes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the North, all <hi>Aegypt</hi> is overflow'd, which because (happening in the midst of July, when the Sun enters into <hi>Leo</hi>) it was believ'd to be the benefit of the coelestiall Lyon, among the Egyptians the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was the Symbole of a floud: and they so made their Aquaeducts, and Conduit-pipes, as that the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were spouted out of the head of a Lyon gaping with open jawes. And from the Egyptian Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tects the Greeks and Romans took up this fashion, from them and other Nations. As also it hath been deriv'd to us from the Egyptians, that upon the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlements of our houses, especially of our Churches, we put the heads and yawning mouths of Lyons. <hi>Vos. l.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 696.</p>
               <p n="32">
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:205034:59"/>(32) <hi>Slow Saturne</hi>] The Planet <hi>Saturne</hi> is twenty nine yeeres, one hundred fifty five dayes, seven houres, thirty six minutes going through the whole Zodiacke. Hence was the originall of the Fable of <hi>Saturn</hi> bound by <hi>Jupiter</hi> his sonne and cast into Hell. Heare we <hi>Lucian</hi> discoursing thereof, <hi>l. de Astrolog.</hi> Neither hath <hi>Jupiter</hi> bound <hi>Saturne,</hi> nor cast him into hell, or done such other things, as men suppose; but <hi>Saturne</hi> is carried in his externall motion at a vast distance from us, and his motion is slow and not easily seen by men. Wherefore they say, hee stands still, as it were bound. And that huge profundity of aire is called Hell. <hi>Voss.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="33">(33) <hi>Mercury to vegetate thy course—]</hi>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Cyllenius rules o're waters that are great,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And consequently o're</hi> Nilus.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O're which when Mercuries proud fires do stand,</l>
                        <l>And in a line direct (as by command</l>
                        <l>Of Phoebe the obeying Ocean growes)</l>
                        <l>So from his open'd fountaine Nilus flowes.
<bibl>May. <hi>Lucan. l. 10.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="34">(34) <hi>Or hath the frozen West restrain'd Thy vernall blasts.]</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>As vainly doth antiquity declare</l>
                     <l>The West winds cause of their increases are—</l>
                     <l>—Their blasts the Rivers current meet,</l>
                     <l>And will not let it to the Ocean get,</l>
                     <l>Prevented so from falling to the main,</l>
                     <l>The stream swels backe, and overflowes the plain.</l>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Idem.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="35">
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:205034:59"/>(35) <hi>Which the world begins the great Ocean—]</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>From th' Ocean swelling which begirts about</l>
                     <l>All lands, some think increased Nile breaks out;</l>
                     <l>The waters lose e're they so far have ran,</l>
                     <l>Their saltnesse quite—</l>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Idem.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="36">(36) <hi>Or hath it stopt the secret way.]</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>Some through the cavernes of earths hollow womb</l>
                     <l>In secret channels think these waters come</l>
                     <l>Attracted to th' Aequator from the cold</l>
                     <l>North clime, when Sol his Meroe doth hold,</l>
                     <l>The scorched earth attracting Water, thither</l>
                     <l>Ganges and Padus flow unseen together:</l>
                     <l>Venting all rivers at one fountaine so</l>
                     <l>Within one channell Nilus cannot go.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="37">(37) <hi>God the world who made, Hath made Nile, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Because it was a custome in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> that the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of the rising of the river <hi>Nilus</hi> should be carried to the Temple of <hi>Serapis,</hi> as it were to the author of the inundation, and increase of the waters; when his image was cast down and burnt, it was generally said that <hi>Serapis</hi> mindfull of the injury would not make the waters flow beyond their wonted channell. But that God might shew it was not <hi>Serapis,</hi> who was much younger then <hi>Nilus,</hi> but that it was him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, who could command the waters of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to increase in their seasons, there was so great an inundation from that time and afterwards, as no age could remember to have been formerly: and therefore
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:205034:60"/> the cubit it self, that is the measure of the water which they call <hi>Pechys,</hi> was from that time wont to bee car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried into the Church to the Lord of the waters. <hi>Ruffin. l.</hi> 2. <hi>in append. ad Euseb. Cassiodorus. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 18.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="commentary">
            <head>Annotations upon the Fourth ACT.</head>
            <p n="38">(38) O <hi>Nubians</hi>] The Chorus of Ethiopian, or black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amore maids sent—
<q>
                  <l>From Nubae's utmost parts through whose</l>
                  <l>Dry land the River Niger flows.</l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Act 1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And which, though the song and Act were ended, staid still upon the stage.</p>
            <p n="39">(39) <hi>Lives the old man] Edward</hi> 1. hearing both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of the death of his son and of his father, wept and lamented much more for his father then for his son, saying to the French King (which asked the cause thereof) that the losse of his childe was but light; for children might after increase and be multiplyed, but the losse of his parent was greater, which could not be recovered. <hi>Fox. Martyrol. vol.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p n="40">(40) <hi>Custome and sharpe lawes, &amp;c.</hi>] If he who shall suffer himselfe to be sold incurre so great hatred; what shall be done unto him that hath sold one against his will or kept him in bondage? the Lawes both of the Jewes and Athenians did punish this wickednesse with death, as it is written by <hi>Moses,</hi> and <hi>Severus
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:205034:60"/> Sulpitius. Dinarchus</hi> tels us, that the Athenians put to death one <hi>Nemon</hi> a Miller, who had stolne an ingenuous child and kept him a bond-slave to work in his Mill. See <hi>Aerodius rerum judieat. l.</hi> 9. <hi>tit.</hi> 7. <hi>De Plagiariis,</hi> where he bitterly inveighs against the Je<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>suites, who under colour of Religion entice children from their parents. And (as you may read in a singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Treatise of his <hi>De Patrio jure</hi>) had inveigled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his own son.</p>
            <p n="41">(41) <hi>Let me him happily requite—]</hi> Maintenance is due likewise to parents; which we are not onely told by the laws, but by a common proverbe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> [taken from the piety of Storkes which requite their parents by feeding them in their old age] So that <hi>Solon</hi> is commended, because upon them who should not doe it he set a marke of infamy. But this is not so ordinary as for the parents to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their children; for children, when they are born, bring nothing with them whereon to live. Besides, they have a longer time to live then their parents: and therefore as honour and obedience is due to the parents and not to the children; so maintenance is due more to the children then to the parents. And the Apostle saith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.14. The children ought not to lay up for the parents, but the parents for the children, <hi>Grot. de jur. bell. ac pac. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 7. § 5. Yet the same Apostle saith, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5 4. Let them (the children or Nephews, I understand with <hi>Beza</hi>) learn first to shew piety at home and to requite their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents. And our Saviour rebukes the hypocrisie of the Pharisees, who by reason of religious oblations thought themselves not bound to relieve their parents, <hi>Marke</hi> 7.12.</p>
            <p n="42">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:205034:61"/>(42) <hi>All Memphis did me their Father call.] Joseph</hi> was but thirty yeeres old when he stood before <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh,</hi> and deserv'd the Title of Father of <hi>Aegypt.</hi> And <hi>Augustus Caesar</hi> was not full foure and thirty yeers of age, when hee was saluted with the goodly name of Father of his country by the Senate and people of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="43">(43) <hi>To them be kind chiefly]</hi> But if any contention or comparison arise, to whom wee owe most duty; in the first place to our Country and Parents, by whose benefits we are most of all obliged; in the next, our children and whole Family which looks upon us onely, and can have no other refuge: then, well agreeing kindred, who for the most part have one common fortune. Wherefore necessary aides of livelihood are most due (as I have said) to them. But life and common conversation▪ counsels, discourses, exhortations, consolations, sometimes also chidings are of most vigour among friends: and that friendship is the most pleasant, which is contracted by likenesse of manners, &amp;c. <hi>Cic. de Offic. l.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p n="44">(44) <hi>The spoiles home of four Kings]</hi> By the Law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture those things are in a just warre acquired by us, which are either equivalent to that which whereas it is due to us wee cannot otherwise attaine, or also which brings damage to him that hurts us within an equall measure of punishment. By this Law <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> gave tithes to God of the spoiles hee had taken from the Kings. <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.16. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.4. <hi>Grot. de jur. bell. ac pac. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 6. § 1.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:205034:61"/>
               <head>Annotations upon the CHORUS.</head>
               <p n="45">(45) <hi>EUphrates]</hi> As in <hi>Asia</hi> by <hi>Perath</hi> or <hi>Prath,</hi> which signifies a River, is meant the River <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which the Greeks call <hi>Euphrates.</hi> So in <hi>Aegypt</hi> is <hi>Nilus</hi> called from <hi>Nachal</hi> which is in Hebrew a Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. <hi>Voss.</hi> See the Note upon <hi>Nile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="46">(46) <hi>Tigris]</hi> So called from the most swift course, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it seemes to equall the swiftnesse of an arrow which the Medes in their language call <hi>Tigris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="47">(47) <hi>In his owne image]</hi> Not of body, but of minde, which consists in immortality, in innocency, and righteousnesse, and other gifts and endowments of the minde. <hi>Vatabl. in Gen.</hi> 1.26. And <hi>Junius</hi> upon the same place saith, That man was made in the image of God, to wit in the nature of the soule, its qualities and attributes. In the nature, for it is an eternall and spirituall, and intelligent essence; in qualities, for man was made after God in righteousnesse, and true holinesse [or holinesse of truth as <hi>Junius</hi> and the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in our English Bible have it] Lastly in the attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, for he obtaineth a dominion or principality in these inferiour things, as it were a certain image of the divine principality. See <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.24. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.10.</p>
               <p n="48">(48) <hi>And sleep his limbes forsake] Adam</hi> should have slept, though he had never sinn'd. For albeit that
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:205034:62"/> sleep had not proceeded from a wearinesse of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriour senses, or the spirits serving them (for neither in that happy state would labour have had place) though also it had not been to repaire the spirits in part consum'd by the naturall heat (for neither would there have bin any losse or decay of strength) yet man had not wanted the pleasure of sleep; because the vapours from the aliment had then also gone up to the brain: the spirits too had bin more inwardly allur'd to a cessation: and thence againe invited to exteriour functions. I am further perswaded to this opinion (which the great <hi>Aquinas</hi> was of) by that sleep sent by God upon <hi>Adam.</hi> I know the Septuagint tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slate it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: and it is a sure argument of an extasy, that with the eyes of his mind he saw a rib taken from him, and <hi>Eve</hi> to be framed thence: so that being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake he forthwith brake out into these words; <hi>This now is bone of my bone, and flesh of my flesh.</hi> Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> though it were an extasie, yet it might bee a slee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> too; In his sleep surely <hi>Adams</hi> minde was divinel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> elevated, so as it saw what was done by God. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>this was confirm'd by the Hebrew word <hi>Tardema,</hi> which signifies a deep sleep. <hi>Voss. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c</hi> 34.</p>
               <p n="49">(49) <hi>The Phaenix] Paulus Fab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us,</hi> and <hi>L. Vitellus</hi> being Consuls, after the revolution of many ages, the Bird <hi>Phaenix</hi> came into <hi>Aegypt:</hi> and afforded mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of discourse upon that miracle to the most lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned both of the inhabitants, and of the Greeks. What they agree in, and many things doubtfull, but not unworthy the knowledge, I have thought sit to set downe. That this creature is sacred to the Sunne, and differing foom others in the beake and feathers, all agree, who have describ'd her forme. Of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:205034:62"/> of her yeeres the report is various. The most common is 500. some affirme 1461. And that the former birds, first in the reigne of <hi>Sesostris,</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of <hi>Amasis,</hi> and then of <hi>Ptolomy</hi> the third of the Macedonian race, flew into the City called <hi>Heliopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> a flock of other birds accompanying them and wondering at the new shape. But antiquity indeed is herein obscure. Between <hi>Ptolomy</hi> and <hi>Tiberius</hi> were lesse then 250 yeeres. Whence some thought this a false <hi>Phaenix,</hi> and not to have come from <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia,</hi> &amp;c. These things are uncertaine and fabulously augmented. But that this bird is sometime seen in <hi>Egypt</hi> is not to be doubted. <hi>Tac. Annal. l.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Phaenix</hi> is said to appeare against a great change in the world. And the Aegyptians paint this Bird, when they would expresse a vicissitude and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stauration of things. <hi>Voss. l.</hi> 2. <hi>in Addend.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="50">(50) <hi>Of whose rare kind but one]</hi> What wise man can believe, there is a single Bird, which burnes her selfe in a fire, kindled both by the Sunne beames and the fanning of her owne wings; that from her turn'd into ashes, or at least from her marrow or blood is bred a worm, which afterwards having taken wings becomes this Bird, repair'd by her owne death, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause she died that she might live, and so is made both the parent and issue: Whence and when fit for the burden, her first care is that (if she spring againe not out of the ashes but marrow or blood) shee carry her parents body to <hi>Heliopolis,</hi> and offer it upon the Altar of the Sun. To have related these things is to have confuted them. Yet that there is such a Bird hath been believ'd even by <hi>Tacitus:</hi> Yea <hi>Tertullian</hi>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:205034:63"/> thought the Scriptures made mention of the <hi>Phaenix.</hi> For in his Book <hi>de Resurrect.</hi> he hath rendred that in <hi>Psalm.</hi> 92. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The just shall flourish as a <hi>Phaenix;</hi> whereas hee should have said, as a Palme tree. With the very like error, as another in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> which <hi>Muretus</hi> observes in <hi>Variis, l.</hi> 13. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. hath translated <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the braine of a <hi>Phaenix,</hi> whereas it signifies the pith of a Palme tree. Surely that <hi>David</hi> meant a plant, is cleare, by that which there follows of the Cedar, and Plane tree. But indeed <hi>Clemens Romanus,</hi> a contemporary with the Apostles, makes mention of this Bird in his first Epistle to the <hi>Corinthians:</hi> Which a few yeeres since came forth into the light by the singular care of that famous man <hi>Patrick Young.</hi> Yet there are, who judge this Epistle to bee none of <hi>Clements,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause by the nature of a Bird, which is no where, he seeks to illustrate those things, which belong to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly truth. But by what we have formerly said of <hi>Pliny</hi> and <hi>Tacitus,</hi> we plainly see that in those times wherein <hi>Clement</hi> liv'd, that opinion of the <hi>Phaenix,</hi> was common. And this is enough in a writing, ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall indeed, yet not appertaining to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of faith, and life. For neither is it necessary that we believe, that <hi>Clement</hi> knew all things, which did concerne the secrets of nature. Nor are we bound to believe it of the Apostles; although Christ promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, <hi>John</hi> 16.13. That he would send the Holy Ghost, who should lead them into all Truth. Surely this is to be restrain'd to the truth of those things, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine to the businesse of salvation. Yea not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to all them, because the Apostles themselves, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 13.9. saw in part, and Prophesied in part: but of all, which it was needfull to know
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:205034:63"/> for the attaining another life. <hi>Voss. Idolol. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 99.</p>
               <p n="51">(51) <hi>The sacred fire]</hi> Was wont to be carried before the King of the Persians, when hee came abroad in publique, in honour of the Sunne, who was adored by them; Which fire was never put out, untill the death of the King. The same ceremony our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor makes <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to use here, the Persian <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thra,</hi> and the Aegyptian <hi>Osiris,</hi> being the same; that is, the Sunne.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="commentary">
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:205034:64"/>
            <head>Annotations upon the Fifth ACT.</head>
            <p n="1">(1) <hi>CElestiall Bull]</hi> It is said of <hi>Joseph, Deut.</hi> 33.17. <hi>His glory is like the firstling of his Bullocke.</hi> Upon which <hi>Junius</hi> and <hi>Tremellius:</hi> Hee performed the duty of an Oxe (whereof <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.4.) when he nourished his Fathers Family in <hi>Egypt.</hi> Wherefore the Egyptians are said to have placed the image of an Oxe next unto the image of <hi>Joseph,</hi> because that the Oxe in tillage doth cooperate with man.</p>
            <p n="2">(2) <hi>The neighbouring Ramme]</hi> But if from the Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians the first signe of the Zodiacke tooke the figure of a Ramme in honour of <hi>Cham,</hi> or <hi>Jove Ammon,</hi> who, to signifie his power, was represented with Rammes hornes: What hinders, but that wee may believe the second signe of the Zodiacke to have took from them the figure of a Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l; and that thereby they understood either the son of <hi>Cham, Osiris,</hi> the same with <hi>Meso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> or <hi>Mizraim:</hi> by whom the Egyptians were taught tillage (the Oxe being the symbole of tillage) or the Patriarch <hi>Joseph,</hi> who for having preserved <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> in a great Famine, did deserve the symbole of an Oxe, and at length came to have divine honours. And in this conjecture concerning <hi>Joseph</hi> you may see the most illustrious and greater then all praise <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi> going before me in his <hi>Sophompaneas,</hi> a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:205034:64"/> where <hi>Pharaoh</hi> is brought in by him thus spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king unto <hi>Joseph:</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>To thee her safety Egypt owes, and I</l>
                  <l>My quiet. That the grounds all wast not lie</l>
                  <l>By men forsaken, that the plow doth lift</l>
                  <l>The earth up to new hopes is all thy gift.</l>
                  <l>And therefore to thy honour I will this</l>
                  <l>Have to be added; as the manner is</l>
                  <l>Of the Eastern Nations, that a place in Heaven</l>
                  <l>Unto thy name among the stars be given:</l>
                  <l>And the field-tiller the coelestiall Bull</l>
                  <l>Of thy full merit shall be made a full</l>
                  <l>And lasting monument: as a place great Cham,</l>
                  <l>Old Mizraims sire hath in the neighbouring Ram.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Which verses I rather recite, because out of that Poem; which as for the argument and handling it is the love and admiration of all good and learned men, is so much more ardently affected, as it is meet it should bee esteemed by mee, unto whose, though undeserving name, that excellent man would have it dedicated and come forth into the light. <hi>Vos. Idolol. l.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 501.</p>
            <p n="3">(3) <hi>Your Majesty]</hi> Our Author hath <hi>Your goodnesse.</hi> The first part of divine worship is to believe that there are Gods. The next, to render unto them their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, to render unto them their goodnesse, without which goodn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sse there is no Majesty. <hi>Seneca Epist.</hi> 99. And <hi>Junius</hi> in his Notes upon <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.18, 19. (where <hi>Moses</hi> doth beseech the Lord to shew him his glory, and is answered: <hi>I will make all my goodnesse passe before thee, &amp;c.</hi>) observes, that the goodnesse of God is his glory.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:205034:65"/>(4) <hi>Heliopolis]</hi> Which signifies the City of the Sunne. It is the same, which is called <hi>On</hi> in the Scriptures, <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.45. <hi>Vossius.</hi> See the Note upon <hi>Asenath,</hi> in the first Chorus.</p>
            <p n="5">(5) —Because your Nation Holds every Shepherd an abomination.] <bibl>
                  <hi>Gen. 43.32.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </p>
            <p>The cause is not there express'd, but by comparing that Text with <hi>Gen</hi> 46.34. and <hi>Exod.</hi> 8.26. it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares that the Egyptians did abhor a Shepherds life, and them who fed upon Oxen, or other cattle; or did sacrifice those creatures which they worshipped for Gods. <hi>Jun. &amp; Tremell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">(6) <hi>And this my head, &amp;c.]</hi> Moreover it was an anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent custome to sweare by naming other things and persons [besides God] whether they did imprecate that they should be hurtfull to them [for perjury] as the Sun, the Earth, Heaven, the Prince; or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they desir'd to be punish'd in them, as in their head, their children, their country, their Prince. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>their was this the custome only of prophane Nations, but also of the Jews, as <hi>Philo</hi> teacheth us. For hee saith, that wee ought not, when we would swear, to run for every thing presently, to the Creator and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Universe; but to sweare by our Parents, Heaven, Earth, the World. The like whereunto is noted by the Interpreters of <hi>Homer,</hi> that the ancient Greeks did not lightly swear by the Gods, but by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things at hand, as by their Scepter: and that this was ordain'd by the most just King <hi>Radamanth</hi> is deliver'd by <hi>Porphyry,</hi> and the Scholiast upon <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ristophanes.</hi> So <hi>Joseph</hi> is read to have sworne by the life of <hi>Pharaoh, Gen.</hi> 42.15. from a custome receiv'd
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:205034:65"/> among the Egyptians, which <hi>Aben Ezra</hi> there notes, <hi>Elizaeus</hi> by the life of <hi>Elias,</hi> 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 2.2. Neither doth Christ, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. as some think, meane that these oathes are lesse lawfull then what are made by the expresse name of God: but whereas the Hebrews did lesse regard them, through a certaine opinion not unlike his, who said, <hi>He thought his Scepter not to be the Gods,</hi> hee sheweth that even these are true oaths. For also <hi>Ulpian</hi> hath said very well: <hi>He who sweares by his owne life, seemes to sweare by God, for he swears with a respect of the Divine Deity.</hi> So Christ shews, that hee who sweares by the Temple, sweareth by God that dwelleth in the Temple, and hee that swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by Heaven, by God, who sitteth thereon, as his throne. But the Hebrew Doctors of those times thought, that men were not bound by oaths made by things created, unlesse, &amp;c.—<hi>Grot. de jur. bell. ac pac. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 13. <hi>De Jure jurando.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">(7) <hi>Israel a wife shall take from Aegypt.]</hi> That is, <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> shall marry <hi>Pharaohs</hi> daughter.</p>
            <p n="8">(8) <hi>A new plantation]</hi> And all the people both small and great, and the Captaines of the Armies arose, and came to <hi>Aegypt,</hi> 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 25, 26.</p>
            <p n="9">(9) <hi>Safe to him an infant exile]</hi> Our author in his <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus Patiens.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>These armes about my neck have hung,</l>
               <l>Coucht on the flowry banks of Nile;</l>
               <l>Aegypt, so just to thy exile,</l>
               <l>Hath now redeem'd her former curse:</l>
               <l>Our Jews then those of Memphis worse.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>G. Sandys.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p n="10">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:205034:66"/>(10) <hi>Pure Religion]</hi> Give me leave to remember a few verses not impertinent, out of that Divine Poet Mr <hi>George Herbert</hi> in his <hi>Church Militant.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>To Egypt first she came, where they did prove</l>
               <l>Wonders of anger once, but now of love.</l>
               <l>The ten Commandements there did flourish more</l>
               <l>Then the ten bitter plagues had done before.</l>
               <l>Holy Macarius and great Antony,</l>
               <l>Made Pharaoh Moses changing th' History.</l>
               <l>Goshen was darknesse, Egypt full of lights,</l>
               <l>Nilus for monsters brought forth Israelites.</l>
               <l>Such power hath mighty Baptisme to produce,</l>
               <l>For things mishapen things of highest use.</l>
            </q>
            <p n="11">(11) <hi>Partakers of so great a good]</hi> The King of <hi>Ethiopia</hi> (said by Geographers to bee one of the greatest Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs in the world) is commonly called <hi>Prester John,</hi> and in the Ethiopick Language <hi>Negush Chavvariav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi,</hi> which (saith <hi>Jos. Scaliger l.</hi> 7. <hi>de emendat. temp.</hi>) doth signifie, The Apostolike Emperor, or the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian King. It is very probable, the Gospel was early planted there, even (as histories report also) by that honourable person the Eunuch, of so great authority under Q. <hi>Candace,</hi> and her Treasurer, who was bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by the Apostle <hi>Philip. Act.</hi> 8.38 Of Ethiopia like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, <hi>Du Bartas</hi> by <hi>Sylvester.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>And scalding quick-sands of those thirsty Plaines,</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Jesus</hi> name yet in some reverence reignes;</l>
               <l>Where Prester John (though part he Judaize)</l>
               <l>Doth in some sort devoutly Christianize.</l>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:205034:66"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Before the Poem.</head>
               <p>IN Mr <hi>Berney's</hi> Verses, for <hi>speakes it own praise only,</hi> read <hi>speake its own praise; only</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Latin prose for <hi>vellat</hi> r. <hi>vellet.</hi> for <hi>injurius.</hi> r. <hi>injurius,</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the Poem.</head>
               <p>Page 9. l. 28. for a <hi>gain:</hi> r. <hi>again.</hi> p. 10. l. 13. for <hi>flow</hi> r. <hi>slow.</hi> p. 28. l. 4. for <hi>Mziraim</hi> r. <hi>Mizraim.</hi> p. 29. l. 11. for <hi>wandring</hi> r. <hi>wandering.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the Annotations.</head>
               <p>Page 46. l. 19. for <hi>Aegyptians</hi> r. <hi>Aegyptians.</hi> p. 56. l. 18. for ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queting; <hi>r.</hi> banqueting, p. 65. l. 22. <hi>for</hi> laugnage; therefore <hi>r.</hi> lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage therefore;</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>